世界中の大勢の人たちと一緒に
We are overjoyed that you are
among the millions around the world
この大会を視聴できていることを
本当にうれしく思います
who are viewing this convention.
東南アジアで聖書を学んでいる
ジョイスという病気の方は
An infirm Bible student named Joyce,
who lives in Southeast Asia,
こうした地区大会について
次のように感謝を表しています
expressed her appreciation
for these arrangements by saying:
“With the convention being streamed online,
「地区大会をオンラインで
視聴できるおかげで
話を漏らさずに聞くことができています
“I don’t have to miss a single talk!
世界中の兄弟姉妹と一緒に
視聴できてうれしいです
“I can watch the program
with the rest of the brotherhood worldwide.
可能にしてくださったエホバに
心から感謝しています」
I am so thankful to Jehovah
for this arrangement.”
皆さんも同じように
感じていることでしょう
Perhaps you can relate to her expressions.
皆さんがdonate.jw.orgや
Thank you for the generous donations
you have made online
他の方法で寄付してくださっている
ことに感謝しています
at donate.jw.org and by other means,
こうしたオンラインのプログラムも
皆さんの寄付によって賄われています
which help make
these streaming services possible.
During these critical last days,
今は難しい終わりの時代なので
many families lack the affection
家庭内でいろいろな問題が生じて
that Jehovah designed us to give and receive.
心が休まらないことが増えています
However, God’s Word contains principles
でも 神の言葉である
聖書の教えに従うなら
that, when followed, lead to peace.
家庭は平和な場所になります
そのことを扱った次のシンポジウムの
興味深い話やビデオを
We’re sure you will enjoy
the fine talks and dramatizations
in this next symposium.
ぜひお楽しみください
奉仕委員会の援助者
ジョエル･デリンガー兄弟が
Brother Joel Dellinger,
a helper to the Service Committee,
最初の話をしてくださいます
will deliver the first talk,
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace
—Show Love and Respect.”
主題は 「家庭の平和に欠かせないもの
愛と敬意」です
家庭の平和は大切なものです
Family peace is precious.
It’s even as the Bible proverb says:
聖書の格言にもこうあります
“Better is a piece of dry bread
where there is peace
「平和な所で1切れの
乾いたパンを食べる方が
than a house full of feasting
along with quarreling.”
言い争いがある家でたくさんの
ごちそうを食べるよりも良い」
But what exactly is family peace?
でも家庭の平和とは何ですか
ある人たちは 「けんかをして
いなければうちは平和だ」と言います
Someone might say, “As long as we’re not
arguing, our family is at peace.”
But is that real peace?
それは本当の平和でしょうか
We might think of two countries
that were fighting
戦争をしていた2つの国が
停戦することに合意したとします
but have now agreed to a cease-fire.
Does the cease-fire mean that they’ve become
それで2つの国は愛し合う
本当の友になったと言えますか
real friends who love one another?
No.
いいえ 本物の平和を築くには
もっと努力が要ります
We know that genuine peace takes more work.
That’s true in the family as well.
家族についても同じです
Our heavenly Father knows
that the most satisfying family peace
天のお父さんが知っているように
本当の意味で平和な家族は
involves more than an absence of arguing.
けんかがないというだけではありません
It involves a family’s well-being and unity.
家族みんなが幸せで
まとまりがあります
そんな平和な家族に今でも
本当になれるのでしょうか
Is such peace in a family today
really possible?
Although none of us have a perfect family,
the answer is yes.
どの家族も完璧ではありませんが
努力するならそれは可能です
While it requires work
—perhaps breaking bad habits
平和を損なう悪い習慣をやめたり
平和に役立つ良い習慣を身に付けたり
that disrupt peace and adopting
new ones that promote it—
those efforts are worth it.
そうした努力には価値があります
In this symposium,
このシンポジウムでは
we’ll see how Bible principles
can guide families to peace,
家族が聖書の原則に従って
どのように平和になるかを考えます
just as a road map
旅行者が地図に従って
美しい目的地に行けるのと同じです
guides travelers to a beautiful destination.
In each of the talks,
we invite you husbands, fathers,
それぞれの話を聞いて 夫 父親 妻
wives, mothers, children, teenagers
母親 子供 若者の皆さんが
to be the traveler who studies the map
旅行者のように地図を調べて
and then goes in the right direction.
正しい道を進めますように
The focus of our first talk
まず最初の話で取り上げるのは
愛と敬意です
is showing love and respect.
Why would you say these two qualities
この2つが家庭の平和に欠かせないもの
と言えるのはなぜですか
are so important to family peace?
Well, it’s simple:
なぜなら 互いに愛と敬意を示す家族は
because family members
who love and respect one another
認められていると感じ
安心できるからです
feel secure and appreciated.
As a result, our relationships
そうすると 家族の絆は温かく
強く 平和なものになります
are warm, close, and peaceful.
Of course, showing love and respect
can be a challenge these days.
でも今の時代 愛と敬意を示すのは
簡単ではありません
In the following dramatization notice why.
その理由を次のビデオで見てみましょう
ねえアイリーン
Irene.
ちょっと見て
Aww,
you look so handsome there.
ああ あなたとてもすてき
Oh, you look beautiful.
君もきれいだよ
Those came out so nice.
よく撮れてるわね
とてもきれいだよ
Look at you.
結婚式
Crazy, right?
That’s the day!
いい一日だったわ
Look at us.
アイリーン すごい驚いてるね
You’re so surprised.
I just knew you were going to do it.
やると思ったのよ！
あ ごめんオリビア 大丈夫だった？
Sorry, Olivia.
Are you OK?
Yeah, it’s OK, Sue.
うん 大丈夫
I’m so sorry.
本当にごめんね
No worries.
うん 平気
Um, I’m all moved in.
全部運べた これでおしまい
That was the last box.
お父さん 結婚式の写真？
Dad, are those the wedding photos?
Yeah.
そうだよ
Let me see.
見せて！
Look it. Here’s . . .
ほら！
ああ みんなきれい
Oh, you all look beautiful.
このドレス すごくいいね
That dress looks so nice.
You look so good.
すごくいい！
ああ この写真！
Aww, look at you.
似合ってた！すごく良かったね
Aww, that suits you.
Very nice, you guys.
全部順調にいったね
Yeah, it all came together.
そうね
It really did.
Yeah.
オリビア
Olivia?
I know this is all new, baby.
いろいろ変わるけど
ちょっと我慢してね
Be patient.
Can I cut in?
先に入れていい？
うん いいよ
Yeah, sure.
Thanks.
ありがとう
What’s wrong?
どうしたの？
Where’s the desk?
机は？
We had to get rid of it.
置く場所がなくなっちゃったから
こっちの方がみんなで使えると思って
This one is better for everyone.
みんなじゃなくて
あの人のためでしょ！
You mean it’s better for him!
マックスのため？どういうこと？
For Max?
What are you saying?
What do you care?
私のことはどうでもいいの？
Don’t talk to me like that. Get back here!
そういう言い方しないで
ねえ ちょっと待って！
ねえオリビア この机どう？
Hey, Olivia, what do you think
about the desk?
Come here, sweetie. Come here.
こっち来て 見てごらん
So you never forget that I love you.
これでオリビアのこと
大好きだって分かるね
I hope you like it.
気に入ってくれるかな？
Today, every family
faces challenges of some sort.
今はどの家族にも
何かしら大変なことがあります
So let’s consult our road map together
では地図を調べましょう
in the Bible at Romans 12:10.
聖書のローマ 12:10を開いて
ご一緒に読んでみましょう
Would you read it with me, please?
That’s Romans 12:10:
ローマ 12:10です
“In brotherly love
「兄弟愛を抱いて
優しい愛情を示し合いましょう
“have tender affection for one another.
In showing honor to one another,
take the lead.”
自分の方から進んで
人を敬ってください」
Now, what’s the point?
ポイントは何ですか
Regardless of the role we play in the family,
家庭でどんな役割があるとしても
一人一人が家族に愛と敬意を持って
接する必要があります
each of us needs to treat our family members
with love and respect.
We need to “take the lead,”
or initiative, to do so.
「進んで」つまり率先してそうします
To help us, let’s consider four good habits
これから良い習慣を4つ取り上げて
どんな努力ができるかを考えます
that all of us should work
to develop more fully.
Habit number one:
1つ目は 優しい愛情を
いつも表すことです
Regularly express tender affection.
When conveyed with sincerity,
心からそうするなら
expressions of affection
愛情の表現は植物にとっての
日光や水のようなものになります
are like sunshine and water to plants.
They help everyone
in the family grow and thrive.
家族みんなが生き生きし
幸せになります
先ほどのビデオで オリビアは
In the video we just watched,
did you note how Olivia
お父さんがくれた緑の机と
優しい言葉を思い返していましたね
cherished her father’s gift (that green desk)
and his tender words?
He told her,
“So you never forget that I love you.”
「これでオリビアのこと大好きだって
分かるね」という言葉でした
We also saw warm affection
再婚した夫婦が子供たちと
結婚式の写真を見ている様子からも
as the newly blended family
of Max and Irene looked at wedding photos.
温かい愛情を感じました
いい雰囲気でした
That was encouraging.
Well, here’s a question: How are we doing
ではどうでしょう 私たちは家庭で
優しい愛情を表しているでしょうか
in expressing tender affection in our family?
If that’s not one of our strengths,
それがあまり得意でないなら
we might relate to a husband
who mustered up the courage
勇気を出して妻に「愛しているよ」と
言った夫の気持ちがよく分かるでしょう
to say “I love you” to his wife.
It brought her to tears—tears of joy.
それを聞いた妻は喜びの涙を流し
こう言いました
And she said this, “I love you too,
「私も愛しているわ
でも あなたがこんなふうに
言ってくれたのは25年ぶりよ」
but this is the first time in 25 years
you’ve said it like that.”
Well, what’s the point?
ポイントは何ですか
We don’t want to wait that long, of course,
そんなに先延ばしするのではなく
but even an awkward attempt
at expressing affection in our family
ぎこちなくても家庭で
愛情を表すようにしましょう
is an act of love,
and it can do so much good.
それは愛の表れで
家族にとても良い影響があります
That’s a habit we all want to cultivate.
みんなが身に付けたい習慣です
Let’s consider a second habit:
では2つ目に行きましょう
Be kind in your actions,
行動も話し方も使う言葉も
親切であることです
tone of voice, and choice of words.
In the video, we recall Irene’s reassurance
to her daughter, Olivia.
ビデオで母親が娘のオリビアを
気遣ってこう言っていました
She said: “I know this is all new, baby.
「オリビア いろいろ変わるけど
ちょっと我慢してね」
Be patient.”
Mom was kind
掛けた言葉もその言い方も親切でしたね
in what she said and how she said it.
A little later, though, Olivia was upset.
その後 オリビアは気分を害しました
While we know she was hurt,
傷ついたのは分かりますが 言葉も
行動も親切ではありませんでしたね
her speech and actions were not so kind,
were they?
During the pandemic,
コロナ禍では 誰もが
大きなストレスを感じているので
all of us have been under tremendous stress,
and likely we didn’t always treat others
家庭でもお互いに思ったように親切に
できなかったということもあるでしょう
in our family as kindly
as we would have liked.
Well, that’s in the past.
でも過去は変えられません
But what can we all do now?
今 何ができるでしょうか
We can pray to Jehovah
to help us “take the lead”
エホバに助けを求めて祈り
「進んで」親切を示すことができます
in showing kindness.
For example,
every day greeting one another kindly,
例えば 毎日家族に明るくあいさつをし
丁寧にお願いをして
「ありがとう」と言い
every day saying “please” and “thank you,”
ちょっとしたプレゼントをし
話す時間を取り
sharing little gifts,
making time to talk, really listening
しっかり耳を傾けること
—all of these are acts of kindness.
この全てが親切の表れです
That’s a good habit we all want to cultivate.
これもみんなが身に付けたい
良い習慣です
3つ目は何でしょうか
What’s habit number three?
Be quick to apologize and forgive freely.
すぐに謝り 寛大に許すという習慣です
In the video, Olivia’s new stepsister, Sue,
ビデオの中で義理の姉妹になったスーが
apologized after she bumped into Olivia
with a box by mistake.
荷物を持っていてオリビアに
ぶつかった時 謝っていました
That apology promoted peace.
そのようにして平和が保たれました
When you and I realize we’ve hurt someone
わざとではなくても 誰かを
傷つけてしまったことが分かった時
even unintentionally, what should we do?
どうすべきですか
すぐに ごめんねと言いましょう
We should make amends quickly.
A mother named Marina said this:
ある母親はこう言っています
「人を許し 腹を立てないという点で
子供に手本を示すよう心掛けています
“We try to set a good example
for our children
“in forgiving others
. . . and not getting offended.
“When I am wrong, I apologize to my children.
自分に落ち度がある時には
子供たちに謝ります
I want them to learn to do the same
in their dealings with others.”
子供が他の人と接する時にも
そうしてほしいと思うからです」
That’s a good habit, wouldn’t you agree?
良い習慣だと思われませんか
Well, let’s consider one more,
a fourth habit:
では4つ目の習慣を考えましょう
Help your family members feel respected.
敬意を払われていると
感じられるようにすることです
An article in the Awake!{
以前の「目ざめよ！」誌に
考えさせられる一言がありました
“Respect is in the eye of the beholder.”
「相手がどう思うかが肝心」
という言葉です
What does that mean?
ほんとですね 自分では家族に
敬意を示していると思うとしても
Even if we think
we’re showing respect in the family,
good questions to ask ourselves are:
こう自問してみるのは良いことです
「家族は敬意を払われていると
感じているだろうか
‘Do my family members
feel that I respect them?
‘Is there more I can do to help my mate,
my children, or my parents
妻や夫 子供や親が
愛され敬われていると感じられるよう
もっとできることがあるだろうか」
feel loved and respected?’
兄弟姉妹 考えてきたような
良い習慣を身に付けて
Brothers and sisters, when we fulfill
our God-given role in the family
家庭で神から与えられた
役割を果たすとき
by developing good habits such as these,
we show respect both for Jehovah
and for all of our family members.
家族みんなとエホバに
敬意を示すことになります
Now, let’s think about Olivia and her mom.
オリビアと母親の話に戻りましょう
In the next video,
note how peace can be restored
次のビデオで愛と敬意によって
どのように平和を取り戻せたか
見てみましょう
by showing love and respect.
It’s OK, Mom.
仕方ないよ
お母さん知らなかったんだし
You didn’t know.
Dad did that for her just before he died.
お父さんが死んじゃう前に
オリビアにしてあげたことだから
何かできることある？
Anything I can do to help?
ローマ 12:10
Romans 12:10:
“In showing honor to one another,
take the lead.”
「自分の方から進んで
人を敬ってください」
Olivia?
オリビア
今日はあなたの好きなもの作ったのよ
I made your favorite tonight.
Thank you.
ありがとう
I wanted to tell you
that I didn’t handle that so well today.
今日私がしちゃったこと
本当に悪いと思ってる
You had good reason
to be upset about the desk.
机のこと 怒るのも無理はないわ
お母さんは知らなかったんだし
Mom, you didn’t know.
It’s just one of those things
that Dad did just for me.
お父さんがくれた特別なものだったの
マックスが新しいお父さんだっていう
ことは分かってるけど
I know he’s my stepdad now, but
I just wish he would have checked first.
せめて捨てる前に言ってほしかった
It wasn’t Max.
捨てたのはマックスじゃないの
私なのよ
It was me.
I wanted to surprise Max
with a place for him to do his work.
マックスのために仕事用の机を置いて
驚かせてあげたかったの
So he didn’t make you get rid of the desk?
じゃあ マックスが捨てるように
言ったんじゃないんだね
No.
違うわ
2人とも私のことなんか
どうでもいいのかと思った
I just thought you both didn’t care.
I will never ever stop caring about you.
オリビアのこと
絶対にそんなふうに思わないわ
とても良い結果になりましたね
What a beautiful outcome!
The well-being and unity
of the family were restored.
家族がまた一つになって
幸せになりました
The mom, Irene,
applied the principle at Romans 12:10.
母親はローマ 12:10の原則を
当てはめました
She ‘took the lead,’ or the initiative,
to talk kindly with her daughter.
「自分の方から進んで」
娘に優しく話し掛けました
Though Olivia was upset,
she too showed love and respect
気分を害していたオリビアも
愛と敬意を示して
母親の話をよく聞きました
by being willing to listen to her mom.
As a result,
the misunderstanding was cleared up,
その結果 誤解はすっかり解けました
気遣われていないと感じていた娘に
and Irene used the opportunity to reassure
her precious daughter of her love,
母親は「オリビアのこと絶対に
そんなふうに思わないわ」と
saying, “I will never ever
stop caring about you.”
言って愛を実感させていました
And how our hearts were touched
娘を抱きしめている場面は
なんだか心が温かくなりましたね
to see their warm embrace!
When we “take the lead”
in applying Bible principles,
このように「進んで」
聖書の原則を当てはめるなら
we promote genuine family peace.
本当に平和な家庭になります
So may all of us be determined
それでこれからも 私たち皆が
to keep showing our family
that we truly love and respect them
家族への心からの愛と敬意を
言葉と行動で示していきましょう
in word and action.
続いて 出版委員会の援助者
ロバート・ルシオーニ兄弟が
Now please listen as Brother Robert Luccioni,
a helper to the Publishing Committee,
considers the next talk
シンポジウムの次の話を
してくださいます
of this symposium, with the theme
主題は「家庭の平和に欠かせないもの
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace
—Improve Communication.”
良いコミュニケーション」です
前の話で考えたように
Our previous talk reminded us
家族が平和を味わうことは
可能ですが 努力が要ります
that it’s possible
for a family to enjoy peace,
but it takes work.
この話では家庭の平和に役立つことを
もう1つ取り上げます
Let’s look at one more step
that can help us stay on the road to peace,
良いコミュニケーションです
and that is good communication.
家族みんなが自由に率直に穏やかに
コミュニケーションを取るなら
A family promotes peace
when all the family members communicate
in an open, calm, and honest manner.
家庭は平和になります
But how does communication help with peace?
コミュニケーションは
平和にどう役立ちますか
Well, a pattern of good communication
keeps a family close.
いつも良いコミュニケーションを
していれば 家族は一致できます
問題が大きくなって平和が乱される前に
It helps us to identify and address problems
before these reach a point
that they take peace away.
それに気付いて解決することができます
Now, that may seem obvious.
それは分かっていても
仕事や学校 集会 奉仕 気晴らし
日常のことなどがあり
But isn’t it true that we may find
that between work and school,
the meetings and ministry,
and recreation and just life in general
家族で会話する時間を取るのが
なかなか難しいと感じるのが
it’s hard to find time
to communicate as a family?
事実ではないでしょうか
Is that a challenge in your family?
あなたの家族もそうですか
In the following dramatization,
次のビデオで どんな習慣が
家族のコミュニケーションの妨げに
なっているか見てみましょう
notice what habits
hinder family communication.
Hey, Steve.
もしもし
ああ兄弟 集会遅れちゃって
すみませんでした
Yeah, I’m sorry I was late to the meeting.
係の仕事 ちゃんとしなきゃ
いけなかったのに
I should have been there
to help out with my assignment.
ちょっと遅れちゃって
Yeah, we got delayed.
We’re late!
早く！みんな 行くわよ
Let’s go, kids!
お待たせ ごめんなさい
We’re coming! Sorry!
Yeah, the family is fine.
はい 家族は元気です
うん みんな一生懸命やっています
Everybody is adjusting really well.
僕の眼鏡 見なかった？
Anyone seen my glasses?
ねえ？
Anyone?
まだみんなのテンポが
合ってない気がしますけど
I mean, we might be a little out of sync,
but I don’t know
まあ どの家族でも
そういうこと ありますよね
—every family has their issues, right?
You going outside in those?
それで出掛けるの？
Mm-hmm.
うん
いろいろありがとうございます
Hey, well, thanks for understanding.
All right.
はい 分かりました
OK. Take care.
失礼します
All right, bye-bye.
コミュニケーションの妨げに
なっていたものに気付きましたか
Did you notice some habits
that hinder family communication?
In the case of this family, it seems like
この家族の場合 電子機器のせいで
technology is stifling their communication.
コミュニケーションが
うまくいっていませんでした
And they obviously have some things
they need to communicate about
話し合うべきことを
話せていませんでした
時間を守ることや服装
気になりましたね
—punctuality, dress and grooming—
but it’s not happening.
Now, while the scenes of them
みんなが自分のスマホを見て
all looking at their devices
and ignoring one another
ほかの人のことを気にしていない様子は
思わず笑ってしまうほどでしたが
may have been a bit humorous,
うちの家族もそういうことが
あると思いましたか
did it remind you of your family at times?
What a good reminder
for us not to let the use of technology
電子機器によって家族との時間が奪われ
関心を払えなくなってしまうことが
ないように ということを学べました
rob our family of our time and attention!
So how can we develop habits
では 良いコミュニケーションに役立つ
どんな習慣を身に付けられますか
that promote good communication?
Let’s consider the second Bible principle
of this symposium.
このシンポジウムの2つ目の
聖書の原則を考えましょう
ご一緒にエフェソス 5章を開いて
Let’s turn together, please,
to Ephesians chapter 5.
15節と16節を読みましょう
And let’s read verses 15 and 16
—Ephesians 5:15, 16:
5:15, 16
“So keep strict watch that how you
「それで 自分の歩み方を
しっかり見守りましょう
“walk is not as unwise but as wise persons,
賢くない人ではなく賢い人のように歩み
時間を有効に使ってください
“making the best use of your time,
今は悪い時代だからです」
because the days are wicked.”
この聖書の原則から
2つの点を考えましょう
Now, let’s look at two ways
that this Bible principle can help us.
1つは 大切なことをきちんと
話し合う時間を取ることです
The first is by making time
to have meaningful communication.
もう一度16節をご覧ください
こうあります
Did you notice there in verse 16
it says “making the best use of your time”?
「時間を有効に使ってください」
Now, the study note for this phrase indicates
脚注からすると 重要なことのために
ほかのことから「良い時を買い取」る
ということです
the need to ‘buy out the time’
for important things
from other pursuits.
これは家族のコミュニケーションに
どう当てはまりますか
So how can this apply
to family communication?
Well, this could include
having a plan, or a routine,
例えば 毎日家族で過ごす時間を
いつ取れるかよく計画し
for when we spend time together
as a family each day.
それを続けることができます
その時間は会話の邪魔にならないよう
And during those times,
we may choose to limit
our use of technology so that it
does not interfere with communication;
電子機器を使わないようにする
というのも1つの方法です
perhaps it’s in the evening
or at a specific mealtime.
夜の時間や食事の時などにそうできます
One brother named Aaron stated,
アーロンという兄弟はこう言います
「一緒に夕食を食べているので
“We have our evening meal together,
家族のそれぞれにとって大切なことを
話したり聞いたりできます
“which allows us time to talk
and hear what’s important
to each member of the family.”
妻と私は予定を調整して
He says: “My wife and I
have arranged our schedules
息子たちを学校に送り迎えし
“so we take the boys
to school and pick them up.
その時間も一緒に過ごしています
This allows us to spend more time with them.”
そして妻と一緒によく散歩をして
And then he says,
“My wife and I regularly take walks
考えていることを自由に話します」
and freely talk about our concerns.”
何を学べますか
What’s the point?
時間を有効に使っていましたね
Well, they’re making good use of their time.
でも そのためにほかのことから
時間を買い取る必要がありました
However, to do this, they’ve had to buy
that time out from other pursuits.
計画を立て 実行していました
But they have a plan; they have a routine.
So, what plan, or routine,
あなたの家族は毎日十分な
コミュニケーションを
取ることができるよう
does your family have
for meaningful communication each day?
どんな計画を立て 実行していますか
もしまだなら やってみませんか
If you don’t have one, can you start now?
Let’s look at the second way
that this Bible principle can help us.
ではこの聖書の原則から
2つ目の点を考えましょう
問題が起きた時 対処するタイミングと
方法を見極めるということです
And that is by determining when and how
to deal with problems when they do arise.
エフェソス 5:15を見ると
You notice verse 15 in Ephesians chapter 5
「賢い人のように歩み」と
書かれています
says that we should ‘walk as wise persons.’
道をよく選び いつ進み いつ止まり
It means we need
to choose our paths carefully,
knowing when to go, when to stop,
when to take another route.
いつ方向転換するかを見分ける
必要があるということです
Well, how can that help us
when problems arise?
これは問題が起きた時
どう役立ちますか
賢い人はたいてい
Well, a wise person
問題を持ち出すのに良い時と
そうでない時を
generally knows when is and when is not
知っているのではないでしょうか
a good time to address a problem.
For example, we all can attest
that when emotions are high,
例えば 感情的になっている時は
問題について話すのに
it’s probably not the best time
to bring up an issue.
ベストなタイミングではない
ということに同意されるでしょう
One father states:
ある父親はこう言います
「気持ちが落ち着くまで
待つ必要があります
“Sometimes we need to wait
and let things cool.
祈ってから一晩寝て翌朝になると
“Often a night’s rest
with prayer makes a big difference
問題に対処しやすくなっていることが
よくあります」
when we address the issue the next morning.”
賢い人ですね
That’s a wise person.
A wise person also listens.
また 賢い人は耳を傾けます
ヤコブ 1:19にある通り
「進んで耳を傾けるべきです
James 1:19 reminds us to “be quick to listen,
すぐに話したり⋯⋯
怒ったりしてはなりません」
slow to speak, [and] slow to anger.”
エホバに祈って助けを求めましょう
Thus, we can go to Jehovah in prayer
and ask him to help us to really listen,
本当に耳を傾けて
穏やかで謙遜でいられるようにです
to stay calm, to stay humble.
ドーンという姉妹はこう言っています
One sister named Dawn states,
「家族の中で問題が起きた時
“When there are problems,
the first thing I do
まず 穏やかに解決できるよう
助けてくださいとエホバに祈ります
is ask Jehovah in prayer to help us
resolve the problem calmly.”
それから問題について
本人と2人だけで話し
Then she says, “Then we talk
with the family member privately
どう感じているか
じっくり聞くようにします」
and really try to listen
to their side of the issue.”
賢い人ですね
That’s a wise person.
賢い人はどんな内容のことを
A wise person will also consider the approach
どんなふうに言うかも
よく考えてから話します
and the words that he or she uses.
「問題がある」と家族の誰かに
指摘するのではなく
For example, rather than telling
our family member that they have a problem,
みんなで取り組まないといけないことが
あるという言い方ができますか
can we turn it around so that it’s something
that we all need to work on together?
Do you reassure your family members
あなたが家族を本当に愛していて
問題についてどう感じているかについて
理解したいと思っていることが
that you really love them
and you want to understand
伝わるような仕方で話しますか
their side of the issue or the problem?
そうするなら家族の誰かを
責めるのではなく
See, now, doing this,
we’re not attacking the family member
一緒に取り組もうとしている
姿勢を示せます
but, rather,
showing that we’re all in this together.
家族のコミュニケーションに
この聖書の原則が役立つことが
So we see benefits of this Bible principle
in communication in our family, don’t we?
分かったのではないでしょうか
2つの点を考えました
1つは時間を有効に使うこと
You notice the two points:
(1) making the best use of our time
もう1つは賢い人のように
歩むことでした
and (2) walking as wise persons.
より良いコミュニケーションのために
努力をしていく必要がありますが
Now, communication will always be
a work in progress,
それには価値があります
but it’s worth the effort,
as it will go a long way
そうすることで
家庭が平和な所になるからです
to bringing peace to your family.
Let’s watch more of our dramatization
先ほどのビデオの続きを見て
良いコミュニケーションに役立つ習慣が
and notice the benefits of developing habits
どのように家族のためになるか
注目しましょう
that promote good communication.
ああ どうしたらいいんだろう？
どう思う？
I don’t know.
What do you think?
みんなで何とかしなきゃ 私もだけど
We all have to work on it.
I know I need to.
いろんな意見が出るかもしれないけど
子供たちと話してみようか
Why don’t we approach it that way
with the kids
—just be open with them?
そうね いいと思う
That sounds like a good idea.
ええと アイリーンとも
話してたんだけどね
OK. So Irene and I have been talking about
コミュニケーションのこと
うちの家族のね
communication
in our family.
スマホとかタブレットについて
話したいと思っているの
We wanted to talk
about our phones and other devices.
僕のことじゃないよね？
You’re not talking about me, are you?
You can’t do that.
そんなの無理！
No, no.
ええ やだ
I know that we can all be
more balanced, but . . .
スマホは絶対必要
これでも使い過ぎないように
してるんだけど⋯⋯
I need it.
You’re joking, right? You mean them.
うそだろ 2人のことでしょ
取り上げないで！
You can’t take them away.
何も悪いことしてないよ
I haven’t done anything bad.
責任持って使うから
I have responsibilities.
Hold on.
ちょっと待って
You’re always on your phone too.
2人もいつも使ってるでしょ
That’s true.
そうだよ
It’s OK.
分かった 一緒に話そう
Let’s just talk about it, all right?
いい？
Sue,
スー
can you read Ephesians 5:15, 16
for us, please?
エフェソス 5:15, 16を
読んでくれる？
「それで 自分の歩み方を
しっかり見守りましょう
“So keep strict watch that how you walk
“is not as unwise but as wise persons,
賢くない人ではなく賢い人のように歩み
時間を有効に使ってください
making the best use of your time,
because the days are wicked.”
今は悪い時代だからです」
じゃあ 僕たちみんなの
スマホの使い方どうかな？
So
how do you think we’re doing
with our phones and other devices?
スマホで悪いことをしているって
言ってるんじゃないのよ
It isn’t that what you’re doing
on your devices is wrong.
そうだよ でも大切なことをする時間が
奪われてしまうことがあるよね
Exactly.
But could it be taking time away
from more important things
—like talking to each other,
家族の会話や
家族の雰囲気に影響したりするかもね
and in that way affecting even
how we’re talking to each other?
そうだね
Yeah, I think it’d be smart
時間を決めて使うって 大事だと思う
to have some boundaries then.
うん 分かった
Yeah, OK.
分かった
OK.
よし じゃあ
どうやってできるか考えよう
OK.
Let’s talk about how we can do that.
お帰り
Hey!
お帰りオリビア
Hey, Olivia.
Hey.
ただいま
Evidently, I haven’t figured out
how to talk to her about her clothes yet.
洋服のこと どう話したらいいか
分からないんだ
Hmm.
うん
I need your help.
頼める？
I got this one.
話してみる
I know,
お気に入りよね でも
クリスチャンらしさでいうとどうかな？
but it’s all about good spiritual judgment.
Do you think that these trends reflect
Jehovah’s view of “respectable dress”?
エホバが喜ばれる
「上品な服装」だと思う？
何が正しいか
あなたなら決められると思う
I know that you’ll do the right thing.
そうしましょう
OK.
オーケー
ねえ 連れてってくれる？
Hey, Gabe, can you take us?
Yeah, of course.
いいよ もちろん
Mm-hmm.
みんなそろってるから
ちょっといい？
While we’re all here,
I know we all have
different views on punctuality,
みんなで時間を守るって 結構難しいね
but
でも 会衆の仕事を果たすために
I really need your help
so that I can take care
of some of my responsibilities.
みんなの協力があると助かるんだ
集会に行く時間 決めていい？
You think we can meet in the middle?
うん
OK.
Yeah.
うん
All right. Great.
良かった 助かる
このシンポジウムでは
家庭の平和に欠かせない聖書の原則を
Now, this symposium has been discussing
four Bible principles
that can guide families to peace.
4つ考えています
デリンガー兄弟が1つ目の
ローマ 12:10を取り上げました
Brother Dellinger considered the first one
at Romans 12:10.
2つ目にこの話では
And in this part, we considered
Ephesians chapter 5,
エフェソス 5:15, 16を
取り上げました
verses 15, 16.
この聖句はビデオに出てきた家族に
どう役立っていましたか
Now, did we see how this scripture
helped our family in the video?
Well, we saw that they knew down deep
that they were not making
時間を上手に使っていないことに
気付き 調整を加えました
the best use of their time,
so they made changes.
頑張っていましたね
良いコミュニケーションを取るために
They saw that they needed to set boundaries
どうする必要があるか
家族で考えていました
so that they could improve
their communication.
We also saw how the family
—the parents—acted as wise persons.
また 親は賢い人として
行動していました
どのようにですか
対処する必要のある問題があった時
How?
Well, by determining when and how
そうするタイミングと方法を
見極めていました
to address the problems
that needed to be addressed,
such as the use of technology,
dress and grooming,
電子機器の使い方 服装
時間を守ることなどについてです
and punctuality.
この聖書の原則は あなたの家族や
Well, can this Bible principle
help your family
私の家族のコミュニケーションに
役立ちますか
—help my family—to improve communication?
この聖句を次回の家族の崇拝で
考えてみるのはいかがでしょうか
Would this be a good scripture to include
in your next family worship?
Now, it takes time to learn how
to communicate well as a family.
家族で良いコミュニケーションが
取れるようになるには時間がかかります
でもそれには価値があります
なぜでしょうか
But it is worth the effort.
Why?
毎日良いコミュニケーションを
取るようにするなら
Well, if we strive to communicate
well each day,
問題が起きた時にも そのことを
お互いに話しやすくなるでしょう
then communication will come more readily
when there are problems.
それで ぜひ家族の
コミュニケーションを良くするために
So be determined to look for ways
to improve communication in your family.
何ができるかを考えてください
この点で率先し
諦めないようにしましょう
And by taking this initiative
and sticking with it,
良いコミュニケーションは
家庭の平和に欠かせないものだからです
you will be following the road map
to family peace.
では統治体のデービッド・
スプレーン兄弟がしてくださる
Please listen now to Brother David Splane,
a member of the Governing Body,
このシンポジウムの次の話に
耳を傾けましょう
as he considers the next talk
of this symposium,
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace
—Work as a Team.”
「家庭の平和に欠かせないもの
みんなで協力する」
エホバは夫婦が協力することを
願っていました
Jehovah intended married couples
to work together.
That’s why Jesus used the expression we find
それでイエスはマタイ 19:6にある
あの表現を使いました
at Matthew 19:6.
聖書から読みましょう
Let’s read this from the Bible
—Matthew 19.
どうぞマタイ 19章をお開きください
And I’ll give you a moment.
19:6
Matthew chapter 19
—now, we’re going to read verse 6.
皆さんも開けたでしょうか
Now, first of all, Jesus quotes
まずイエスは創世記 2:24から
引用しています
from Genesis 2:24.
Speaking of married couples, he says:
夫婦についてこう言っています
「2人はもはや別々ではなく
一体です」
“So that they are no longer two,
but one flesh.”
Now, you remember, Jehovah
made that comment in the garden of Eden.
これはエホバがエデンの園で
語った言葉です
But now Jesus adds something
that isn’t in Genesis.
でもイエスは創世記にない言葉を
付け加えてこう続けます
He says: “Therefore, what God has yoked
「ですから 神が結び合わせた
“[yoked] together,
［脚注では 「くびきでつないだ」］
ものを 人が離してはなりません」
let no man put apart.”
When we think of a yoke,
we may think of a team of horses
くびきとは 畑を耕したり
荷車を引いたりする
plowing a field or pulling a heavy wagon.
2頭の動物をつなぐ横木です
Well, if they pull together,
they can be a powerful force.
2頭が協力すれば
たくさんのことができます
The same is true
when family members work together.
家族が協力するときにも
同じことが言えます
Mom, Dad
お母さん お父さん
—you have excellent reasons to work together.
お二人が協力するのは
とても良いことです
When you work together,
you contribute to the peace of the family.
協力するなら 家庭は
平和な所になります
And think of the effect
it has on the children.
お子さんにも良い影響があります
By working together, you’re teaching
that fine young son of yours
お二人の協力する姿を見て
息子さんは思いやりのある夫また父親に
how to be a caring husband and father,
and your beautiful daughter how to be
a supportive wife and mother.
娘さんは支えになる妻
また母親になるでしょう
But what happens when teammates
begin pulling in opposite directions
では くびきでつながれた動物の一方が
別の方向に引っ張ったり
or when one puts on the brakes?
止まったりしたら どうでしょうか
Let’s watch a video.
家族の場合どうなるか
ビデオを見ましょう
Now, here’s the setup.
長いこと姉妹は1人で2人の子供を育て
For a long time, a sister raised
her two children as a single parent,
and she did a great job of it.
とてもよくやっていました
Then she married a very kind brother.
そして優しい兄弟と結婚します
The family has a new head.
夫が頭になります
Let’s see how well the sister
is adapting to her new role.
姉妹がそれにどれほど順応
できているか見てみましょう
The last few weeks of family worship
have been nice,
ここ何回かの家族の崇拝
良かったわよね
right?
Yeah.
うん
All these things we ask and pray
in Jesus’ name, Amen.
イエスの名を通して
お祈りします アーメン
Amen.
アーメン
じゃあ 今週は⋯⋯
OK, this week . . .
We are in chapter 5.
5章だったわよね
Yep, that’s right.
うん そうだったね 先週は
ガブリエルだったから 今週は⋯⋯
And last week, Gabe read, so this week . . .
It’s Sue’s turn.
スーが読む番
That’s right.
It’s Sue’s turn.
そうだね スーの番だ
OK, the point here is
that when it comes . . .
そうだね この要点は⋯⋯
Honey, maybe an illustration would be better.
あなた ここはたぶん例えがいいと思う
ああ そう
Um, OK.
例えば 鳥は⋯⋯
It’s like a bird . . .
オリビア これではっきり
分かったらいいんだけど
Well, hopefully I was able to clear that up
for you a little bit, Olivia.
Yeah. Thank you.
うん ありがとう
ねえマックス 違うと思う
Well, actually, Max, that’s not true.
最近の「ものみの塔｣で
新しい理解になったわよね
We had an updated understanding
in the recent Watchtower.
あっ そうだね
Thanks.
I think they went really well, right?
良かったと思わない？
ねえ？
Um, actually . . .
うーん そのことなんだけど⋯⋯
Hey.
あら
Maybe we can talk about it later.
後で話そうか
OK.
うん 分かった
The sister isn’t a bad person.
姉妹は悪い人ではありません
But we can ask:
What is she teaching her daughter
ですが 娘は妻の役割について
何を学ぶでしょうか
about the wife’s role in the family?
And what is her son learning
about taking the lead
息子は家族をまとめることについて
何を学びますか
as the man of the house?
He hasn’t had a man
in his life for a long time.
長い間 息子には父親がいませんでした
Now there is one.
でも今はいます
It’s safe to say that the kids
will stand a better chance
両親が力を合わせているのを見るなら
of having a successful marriage themselves
将来子供たちも幸せな結婚生活を
送りやすくなるのではないでしょうか
when they see their parents pulling together.
A little later, we’ll see how
the husband handles the situation,
後ほど 夫がこの状況を
どう扱うかを見ます
and we brothers
are going to want to pay attention.
兄弟たちはぜひ注目してください
これは必見です
This is a classic.
お父さん お母さん 子供たちが
Family life is more pleasant when Dad, Mom,
チームとしてみんなで協力するなら
爽やかになります
and the kids work together as a team.
The family head is the captain.
お父さんがキャプテンです
そしてキャプテンは
He needs to make sure that everyone knows
チームがどんな目標に向かっていて
what goals the family is working toward
それぞれがどのように貢献できるかを
and how each one can contribute
toward achieving those goals.
みんなが分かっているようにすべきです
When it’s your family’s turn
to help clean the Kingdom Hall
例えば 王国会館や大会会場の
清掃に参加する機会があるなら
or a convention venue, for example,
子供たちを家に置いて
いかないでください
don’t leave the kids at home.
They’re part of the team.
お子さんもチームの一員なので
ぜひ連れていきましょう
Don’t go there with half the team.
Let them experience the joy
that comes from serving others.
ほかの人に仕えることから来る
喜びを味わえるよう
Let them work along with you.
一緒に働いてください
If you’re assigned to clean the restrooms,
トイレ掃除を割り当てられても
don’t complain about it—a very fine example.
文句を言ったりせず
手本を示しましょう
Your children will learn that when
there’s work to be done, we just do it.
お子さんはやるべきことがあれば
何でもするということを学べます
We aren’t picky about what we will
and will not do.
私たちは あれはする これはしないと
選り好みはしません
And we don’t feel
that some jobs are beneath us.
あの仕事をするのは恥ずかしいと
思ったりはしません
Now, this is in line with Paul’s counsel
こうした考え方は
フィリピ 2:3, 4にある
found at Philippians 2:3, 4.
パウロのアドバイスと一致しています
Let’s look that up.
開きましょう
It’s good exercise
見つかりますか
—Philippians chapter 2,
フィリピ 2:3, 4
verses 3, 4.
家族で協力することを
考えていますが こうあります
Now, we’re thinking about the family
as a team here.
It says: “Do nothing out of contentiousness
「対抗心を抱いたり 自己中心的に
なったりしてはなりません
“or out of egotism,
“but with humility consider
others superior to you,
謙遜になり 自分より他の人の方が
上だと考えてください
“as you look out
not only for your own interests,
自分のことばかり考えずに
他の人のことにも
but also for the interests of others.”
気を配りましょう」 いいですね
やるべき仕事があれば
誰かがしなければなりません
When there’s work to be done,
someone has to do it.
Do I think that I’m so special
that someone else has to look after it?
自分は特別だから それをほかの人が
やるべきだと考えますか
Some families volunteer
to help with Kingdom Hall maintenance.
ある家族は王国会館の
メンテナンスを手伝っています
When the kids are old enough,
they can work on other projects
子供が大きくなったら
大会ホールでの奉仕も行えます
like working on an Assembly Hall.
楽しいですよ
They have a ball!
The friendships that you
and your young people will forge
あなたもお子さんも仲間と
生涯続く友情を築けます
can last a lifetime.
And here’s a bonus: When the young people
ボーナスもあります お子さんは
巡回大会や地区大会に行った時
go to a circuit assembly
or a regional convention,
一緒に働いた人たちと再会して
they’ll have good friends to associate with
いろいろな年代の仲間と
—both young and old—
people they’ve been working with.
良い交友を楽しむことができます
家の仕事についてはどうですか
What about working around the house?
Some parents feel that the children
shouldn’t have to help out at all
子供は学校の勉強があるから
お手伝いをさせるべきでは
ないと考える親もいます
because they have their schoolwork to do.
でも学校の勉強は
自分のためにするものです
But their schoolwork is something
they do for themselves.
How are they contributing
to the welfare of the family?
家族のために何か
できることがあるでしょうか
How are they learning
to serve others unselfishly?
ほかの人に仕えることを
どのように学べますか
It’s good for a child to feel that he has
an important role in the household
子供たちにはぜひ
家庭で大切な役割があり
人の役に立てると感じてほしいものです
and that people are counting on him.
Think what that does for his self-respect.
そうすれば 子供たちは
自尊心を持てます
A father named Steven said,
スティーブンという父親はこう言います
「親が手伝いを何もさせない子供は
“When nothing is expected of them,
“children learn that they
are here to be served,
何でもしてもらえると思い込み
人生で求められることに関して
“and they grow up with a distorted view
of what life will require of them.”
正しい見方のできない大人になります」
We might ask, Would a young person
では そういう若者が仕事を
続けられると思いますか
with that attitude
even be able to keep a job?
When some in the world lose their job,
世の中には職を失った後
they remain unemployed for a long time.
長いこと失業したままの人もいます
They can’t pay the bills.
生活費が払えません
実は求人はいろいろあるのですが
Yet, there are job opportunities
all around them,
but they consider those jobs beneath them.
その仕事をするのは
恥ずかしいと言うのです
And what’s one of the most annoying traits
an employee can have?
非常に厄介な従業員とは
どんな人でしょうか
Ask any boss.
よく言われるのは
何かをお願いされると
When the worker is asked to do something,
he replies,
「それは自分の仕事じゃない」と
答える人です
“That’s not my job.”
Teach your child that anything
that needs to be done
お子さんに 年齢的にも能力的にも
自分にできる仕事を
is his job if he’s old enough
and capable of doing it.
何でも行うように教えていきましょう
How early should parents
start to assign chores to their children?
何歳ごろからお手伝いを
させたらいいと思いますか
Some experts have found that children who are
3歳あるいはそれより小さい子供にも
three years old or even younger
お手伝いをするよう教えることができる
と述べる専門家もいます
can be taught to help out.
They can learn to pick up their toys,
clean up spills, sort laundry.
おもちゃを片付けたり 洗濯物を
たたんだりすることができます
Older children can vacuum,
少し大きくなったら 掃除機かけ
wash the car, prepare a meal.
洗車 料理を手伝えます
I’m happy to say that many young brothers
here at Bethel
うれしいことに ベテルには料理の
とても上手な若い兄弟がたくさんいます
are excellent cooks,
which is often the result
それはたいてい親の
良い訓練のおかげです
of fine parental training.
Do you remember the video where Caleb
カレブがおもちゃを片付ける
ことについて教えてもらっている
is taught to clean his room
and put away his toys?
ビデオを覚えていますか
That video was a game changer
for many children.
そのビデオを見てたくさんの
子供たちが変わりました
They want to be just like Caleb.
みんなカレブのように
なりたいと思いました
And now when you enter their room,
you can find the bed.
今では部屋に入ると
ちゃんと床が見えます
問題が起きた時
互いを責めてはなりません
When problems arise,
attack the problem, not each other.
大切なのは 自分にとっていいか
ではなく 家族にとっていいかです
It’s not ‘How can I win?’
but ‘How can we win?’
You’ll see an excellent example of that
in the follow-up video.
この点で素晴らしい手本を
ビデオで見ることができます
Let’s watch.
ご覧ください
Hey!
お茶持ってきた 飲む？
Want some tea?
Sure!
ありがとう
Hey, babe,
ねえアイリーン 僕たちチームだよね
you and me, we’re a team, right?
Yeah, of course!
もちろんそうよ
これを読んで
僕たちのことを考えていたんだ
When I read this, I thought about us.
「それで ２人はもはや
別々ではなく 一体です」
“So that they are no longer two,
but one flesh.”
僕と結婚する前 君は長いこと
全部自分で背負ってきたよね
I know that before, you had to shoulder
everything yourself for so long.
うん
Mm-hmm.
よくやってきたね
And you did great.
2人を エホバを愛するいい子に
育ててきたね しかも一人で
You’ve been raising two beautiful,
spiritual kids on your own.
でも今は僕がいる
But now you have me.
うん そうね
Yeah, I do.
So do you think
sometimes we’re not a team?
でも 時々チームじゃなく感じる
っていうこと？
いや ただ時々家族の崇拝で⋯⋯
Well, it’s just that sometimes
during family worship . . .
楽しくてつい割って入っちゃうのよね
もう私ったら！
I get excited, and I jump in. I know!
何年も私が家族の崇拝やってきたから
I’m just so used to doing it
after all these years.
I know you’re not trying to take over.
君が仕切ろうとしているって
言ってるんじゃないんだ
And listen, I love the way you teach.
君の教え方はすごくいいよ
I see how you can reach the kids
僕には思い付かないような仕方で
よく教えている
in ways that I can’t.
司会は僕だけど
これからもサポートしてほしいんだ
Just let me guide it,
and I’ll make sure you can do that.
Thanks, honey. Thanks for your patience.
ありがとう いろいろ辛抱してくれて
僕の方こそ 君に感謝してる
No, thank you for your patience.
I’m a work in progress,
but we make a great team.
まだまだ努力中だけど
いいチームになれるよ
次の家族の崇拝の前に
一緒に内容を見ておこうか？
Why don’t we look at what we’re going
to cover before our next family worship?
That sounds great.
それはいいわね
Wasn’t that a fine example
妻を責めることなくどのように
問題に取り組むか
of how to attack a problem and not your mate?
良い手本でしたね
No arguments, no raised voices,
議論せず 声を荒げず
no accusations
—the husband had empathy for his wife.
非難しませんでした
夫は妻に感情移入していました
He didn’t question her motives.
動機を疑ったりせず
He realized that as a single parent,
妻がシングルマザーとしてずっと
よくやってきたことを認めていました
she’d been taking the lead for a long time.
And notice how she responded
to her husband’s kind counsel.
夫の言葉に対する
妻の反応も良かったですね
No doubt it’s going to be easy
for the kids to respect their stepfather,
きっと子供たちは父親に
敬意を払いやすくなり
夫と妻が互いにどう接し
and they’re going to learn
how a husband and wife
どう協力するとよいかを学べるでしょう
should treat each other
and how they should pull together.
Sometime soon, you might want
to consider these questions:
ぜひ早いうちに 次の点を
話し合ってみるのはどうですか
In what aspects of our marriage
do we work well as a team?
うちの家族はどんな点で
互いによく協力しているだろうか
And then, how can we improve?
もっとできることがあるだろうか
It pleases Jehovah
家族がチームとして
みんなで協力するなら
when family members work together as a team.
エホバは喜ばれます
That promotes peace in the family.
家庭は平和になります
And our God is a “God of peace.”
そうです 私たちの神は
「平和の神」です
Now Brother John Ekrann
次にジョン・エクラン兄弟が
シンポジウムの最後の話をします
will consider the final talk
of this symposium,
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace
主題は「家庭の平和に欠かせないもの
—Worship Jehovah Together.”
一緒にエホバに仕える」です
エホバは家族の幸せと
平和を願っています
Jehovah wants your family
to be happy and peaceful.
But Jehovah does more than simply say,
でも 「平和な家族に
なれるといいですね」と
“I hope you have a peaceful family life.”
言っているだけではありません
He explains exactly how we
can get our family there.
そのためにどうする必要があるか
説明しています
I want you to imagine Jehovah
laying out a map in front of you
エホバはあなたに地図を見せて
こう言っているかのようです
and saying: “See these landmarks?
「これが目印です 平和への道で
それを見つけてください
“Look for them on the road to peace.
And if you see them,
you’re going in the right direction.”
それが見えたら正しい方向に
進んでいます」
So far in this symposium, we’ve passed
このシンポジウムで幾つかの
目印を見てきました
the landmarks of showing love and respect,
愛と敬意 良いコミュニケーション
improving communication,
みんなで協力することです
and working together as a team.
The last landmark
we’ll consider in this symposium
このシンポジウムで最後に目指す目印は
is worshipping together as a family.
エホバに家族で一緒に仕えることです
一緒にエホバを崇拝するなら
家庭は平和になり 祝福を受けます
Worshipping together as a family
promotes peace and brings his blessing.
Even if not all in your family
are worshippers of Jehovah,
家族みんながエホバに仕えていなくても
クリスチャンの良い習慣を守るなら
you can promote peace
by maintaining a very good spiritual routine.
家庭はもっと平和になります
In the following dramatization,
notice some common obstacles
次のビデオで 家族でエホバを
崇拝する時 ありがちなことを
to worshipping Jehovah as a family.
ちょっと見てみましょう
Hi.
うーん どうしたの？
Hey, babe.
うん ちょっと
今週の家族の崇拝
何にするか決まった？
So, what’s for family worship this week?
I think I got some good ideas.
一応 良さそうなのを見つけたよ
Yeah?
ほんとに？
Mm-hmm.
うん
Thank you for reading that.
朗読ありがとう えっと
Um.
じゃあ 次は質問読んでみようかな
Let’s just go ahead and ask the question.
We’ll just do that.
13, 14 「どうすれば惜しみなく
与えることができますか」
So paragraphs 13 and 14:
“How can we be generous?”
誰か 分かる？
Anybody?
今読んだ脚注から
この性質にどういう意味があるか
Now, the footnote that we just read
really helps us to appreciate
ということが本当によく分かるね
the definition of that quality.
この定義がないと
言葉の意味がはっきり分からないし
Without the definition, we’re left to wonder
exactly what it is
and how it connects to the other things
今晩学んでいることとのつながりも
よく分からないね
that we’ve discussed this evening.
Gabe, can you go ahead
and read the next one for us?
ガブリエル 次の節 読んでくれる？
Mm-hmm.
うん
Thank you.
ありがとう
The Bible contains many examples
of submissive individuals.
聖書には従う点で手本になった人たちの
ことが幾つも記録されています
So are there examples?
聖書には手本が載っているかな？
Sue.
スー
Yeah.
載ってます
That’s right.
そうだね 手本と言っても
いろいろあるね
When we talk about examples,
where do we start?
There are examples in the past;
過去の手本もあるし
there are even examples presently.
今の時代の人たちも手本になるね
And we could even be examples.
僕たちも手本になれるんだ
That’s—that’s the power of them.
手本って大事なんだよ
Let’s keep going.
次 行こう
なんか読んでばっかりだったね
That was a lot of reading.
I know, right?
そうだね
家族の崇拝 楽しみたいとは
思ってるんだけど
I want to enjoy family worship, but
I feel like the things that we are covering
やってる内容があんまり
今の自分に必要だって感じなくて
are just really not what I need right now.
そうだね
Yeah.
子供に今必要なことだったかな？
You know, I just don’t know
if this is what they need right now.
Hmm.
うん 一緒に考えましょ
We’ll keep working on it.
I think we’d all agree that family worship
was difficult to watch.
この家族の崇拝は
見ていられないと思ったでしょうか
It was uncomfortable for everyone.
何とも気まずい感じでした
Clearly, Max and Irene had some obstacles
明らかに 子供たちが
家族の崇拝を楽しめるよう
they needed to overcome
to really worshipping Jehovah as a family.
両親には改善すべきことがありました
To start and keep a good habit going
良い習慣を始めるのも続けるのも
requires determination and resolve.
強い決意が要ります
So that’s where you need
to start for your family.
そこがスタート地点です
You need to resolve
家族で一緒にエホバに
仕えるという決意が必要です
that you’re going
to worship Jehovah as a family.
Notice the resolve in Joshua’s words
ヨシュア 24:15の
言葉に表れている
at Joshua 24:15.
ヨシュアの決意に注目しましょう
That’s Joshua 24:15:
ヨシュア 24:15です
“Now if it seems bad to you to serve Jehovah,
「もしエホバに仕えることが
良くないと思えるなら
“choose for yourselves today
whom you will serve,
川の向こうで父祖たちが
仕えた神々であれ
“whether the gods that your forefathers
served on the other side of the River
今住んでいる土地の
アモリ人の神々であれ
“or the gods of the Amorites
in whose land you are dwelling.
誰に仕えるかを今日自分で選びなさい
“But as for me and my household,
しかし 私と私の家の者は
we will serve Jehovah.”
エホバに仕えます」
Yes, worship of Jehovah as a family
家族でエホバを崇拝することが
needs to be at the very center
of your family life.
家族の生活の中心にあるべきです
Now, weekly family worship
それは毎週の家族の崇拝を
行うというだけのことではありません
is not all that’s involved
in worshipping together as a family.
Let’s consider five ways
5つの方法を取り上げ
どうすれば家族でエホバに一緒に
仕えられるか考えましょう
we can worship Jehovah together as a family.
(1) Prayer.
1つ目は祈りです
Parents, do not underestimate the impact
親の皆さん 皆さんの祈りが
お子さんに与える影響を
過小評価しないでください
that your prayers have on your children.
When a child hears their parents
pour out their hearts to Jehovah,
親がエホバに心から祈るのを聞いて
子供はエホバが現実の
存在であることを理解します
that tells them that Jehovah
is very real to their parents.
I can recall growing up listening
to my father’s prayers.
私も父親の祈りを
聞いていたのを思い出します
Now, when I was young,
I thought his prayers were very long.
小さい時は とても長い
祈りだと思っていました
But as I grew older and really
listened carefully to what he was saying,
でも 大きくなって祈りの内容を
本当によく聞くようになると
I could see how much of a close relationship
he had with Jehovah.
父親がエホバとどれほど
親しいのかがよく分かりました
(2) Discuss the daily text.
2つ目は日々の聖句です
It’s an excellent habit
エホバのことを考えて
1日を始める良い習慣です
and a very spiritual way to start the day.
(3) Attend meetings.
3つ目は集会です
Now, we’re not just making sure our family
is there at the meetings
家族が集会に出席しているかだけでなく
集中して参加しているかが大切です
but that they’re involved and engaged.
And work hard to prepare
so that all family members
しっかり準備して 家族みんなが
よく考えたコメントを
できるようにしましょう
can have a meaningful comment
at the meetings.
(4) Share in the ministry regularly
as a family.
4つ目は 定期的に家族で
伝道することです
Now, sharing in the ministry together
as a family
家族で一緒に伝道を行うと
仲が深まるのではないでしょうか
draws us closer to our family members.
When we hear them speak about the truth,
家族が真理について語り
we listen to their phone calls,
電話で話すのを聞き
or we read their letters,
書いた手紙を読む時
we can feel their faith.
信仰を感じます
I loved going in the ministry with my mother
私も母親と一緒に伝道に行き
and listening to her skillfully use the Bible
上手に聖書を使って質問に
答えているのを聞くのが好きでした
to answer questions.
And (5) have a consistent,
5つ目は 定期的に楽しい
enjoyable,
and meaningful Family Worship program.
有意義な家族の崇拝を行うことです
Let’s consider what that means
—first of all, consistent.
考えていきましょう
まず定期性です
In the video, Max was trying to have
ビデオで父親は毎週定期的に
行おうとしていました
the family worship consistently each week.
Is your family worship consistent each week?
皆さんの家族の崇拝はどうですか
Is your family worship enjoyable?
楽しいことも大切です
In the video, the kids were bored.
ビデオで 子供たちはつまらなそうで
They were looking at their phones
and checking the time.
スマホをいじったり
時計を見たりしていました
And week after week
of kind of a question-and-answer style
毎週 質問と答えの
スタイルが続いていたので
子供たちは一言答えを
言うだけになっていました
led to the young people
giving sort of one-word answers.
It did not look enjoyable.
楽しそうではありませんでした
Now, would your family
describe family worship as enjoyable?
皆さんの家族は家族の崇拝を
楽しいと感じていますか
How about meaningful?
次は有意義かどうかです
What Max was using for material
父親が使っていた資料は
was material that he thought was meaningful.
自分が有意義だと思うものでした
But did it look like it
was meaningful to the family?
でも家族にとって有意義なものに
見えましたか
Does your family worship use material
that is meaningful to your family?
皆さんは 家族にとって有意義な
資料を使っていますか
Now, after reviewing these five points,
5つの点を考えてきましたが
良い習慣を維持するのが
難しいと感じるとしても
we don’t want you to be discouraged
if it’s a struggle
to maintain a good routine.
どうぞ落ち込まないでください
Life in this system has many challenges,
今の生活には 問題や試練
trials, and unexpected events.
予想しないことがいろいろ起きます
So stay positive.
前向きに取り組みましょう
And when your good routine
breaks down from time to time,
時々良い習慣が乱されるとしても
consider what adjustments you can make
どう調整すればよいのか考え
to be successful and get
your spiritual routine back on track.
家族で一緒にエホバに仕える
良い習慣を取り戻してください
Regularly ask Jehovah for his help,
and don’t give up.
エホバにいつも助けを求めて
諦めないようにしましょう
Now, as you watch
the following dramatization,
ではビデオの続きを見て
notice how Max and Irene
and the family worked together
良い家族の崇拝ができるよう
両親と子供たちがどのように
協力するかに注目してください
to make family worship successful.
March 15, 2014, Watchtower,
「ものみの塔」2014年3月15日号
“Family Worship
—Can you Make It More Enjoyable?”:
「家族の崇拝
もっと楽しく行なえますか」
“The worship of Jehovah
should not be boring. . . .
「エホバの崇拝は
退屈なものであってはなりません
Address the needs of each family member.”
⋯⋯それぞれの子どもの
必要に注意を向ける」
Babe, what do our kids need?
うちの子たちの必要は何だろう？
What’s actually going on in their lives?
何に関心があるんだろうね？
Family worship needs to include that.
それを家族の崇拝で扱えたらいいね
Yeah, maybe we need to pay more attention
to what’s going on with them.
そうね
子供たちともっと会話して
何を考えているのか
聞くといいのかもしれないわね
Talk to them; listen to them.
I’m going to send you a link
to a great Watchtower{
この記事のリンク送っておくよ
うん 読んでみる
I can’t wait to read it.
Max and I changed our approach.
2人で取り組み方を変えた
We found out what mattered to our kids
子供たちがどんなことで
悩んでいるかが分かった
—like friends,
友達のこととか⋯⋯
ステップファミリーとして
どうやっていくかとか⋯⋯
. . . adjusting to a blended family,
. . . dating.
デートのこととか
家族の崇拝のやり方を変えて
So we turned things around
and used family worship
to focus on what our kids really needed
子供たちが本当に必要と
思っていることを扱うことにした
そして 将来試練が降り掛かるときに
どうすればよいかも考えた
and to prepare ourselves
for possible future trials.
Good night, y’all.
おやすみ
Good night.
おやすみなさい
Um,
ああ あのさ
家族の崇拝 すごく良かった
family worship was—was cool.
It was.
うん 良かった
I’m glad you liked it.
それは良かった
ありがとう
Thank you.
Good night, y’all.
おやすみ
Night.
おやすみなさい
Good night.
Hey! Guess what?
ねえ 聞いてよ
What?
何？
I applied to Bethel.
ベテル申し込んだんだ
You did?
ほんとに？
うん
Yep.
That’s really exciting.
うわ 楽しみ！
すごいね
I’m proud of you.
ありがとう
Thanks.
Aww, congratulations.
頑張ってね
ありがとう
Thank you.
Hey, it’s selfie time, everybody.
Come on, let’s get together.
じゃあ みんなで写真撮るよ
こっち来て
All right. On three
we’re going to say Bethel, OK?
1 2 3でベテルって言ってね
いい？ はい オッケー
いくよ
All right.
One, two, three.
1 2 3 ベテル！
Bethel!
We’ve come a long way.
いろいろあったな
And through it all,
でも エホバはいつも
愛を示すことを教えてくれた
Jehovah has taught us to love
それに 家族に欠かせないものをくれた
and he’s given our family
peace.
それは平和
両親は家族の崇拝について
何が良くなかったかを分析し
We can see that Max and Irene analyzed
what was wrong with family worship
and decided to change their approach.
やり方を変えていましたね
Let’s examine how they did that
and what it means for us.
その方法から何を学べるかを
考えてみましょう
What did they do to make their
家族の崇拝をもっと有意義なものに
するため 何をしていたでしょうか
family worship more meaningful?
Well, Max and Irene had to ask themselves
2人は子供たちの生活に何が
起きているかを考える必要がありました
what was going on in their kids’ lives.
What topics could they
discuss at family worship
どんなテーマを家族の崇拝で
取り上げれば
子供たちに本当に役立つかを考えました
that would truly be useful to their kids?
Did you smile when you saw Max
almost drop the glass
娘がデートについて話した時
お父さんがコップを落としそうに
なったのに気付きましたか
when his daughter talked about dating?
But what a difference their efforts to listen
話を聞き 子供たちのことを
よく理解しようと努力した時
and really understand what was happening
家族の崇拝はぐっと良くなりました
with the kids made in the family worship!
How did Max and Irene
make family worship more enjoyable?
両親は家族の崇拝を
楽しいものにしていました
Did you see how the family
was reacting at family worship now?
家族の崇拝の時の
みんなの様子はどうでしたか
What a difference!
全く違っていました
子供たちは笑顔でした
The kids were smiling.
They looked engaged in the discussion
みんな内容に引き込まれ
and touched by what they were discussing.
心が動かされている様子でした
So do what you can
to make sure that your family
では 家族がリラックスして
楽しめるよう
feels relaxed and happy
家族の崇拝が幸せと喜びにあふれた
エホバにふさわしいものになるよう
and that your family worship reflects
the kind of happy
and joyful God that Jehovah is.
できることを行いましょう
Remember, your family will often remember
皆さんもおそらく家族の崇拝で
学んだ細かなことよりも
more about how they felt
during family worship
その時どう感じたかを
思い出すことの方が多いでしょう
than maybe the exact details
of what they learned.
Keep worshipping Jehovah as a family.
家族でエホバに仕え続け
Make your family worship consistent,
家族の崇拝を定期的に
enjoyable, and meaningful.
楽しく有意義に行いましょう
And work together to overcome obstacles,
調整が必要な時は協力しましょう
just like Max and Irene and the kids
all worked together to solve problems
ビデオに出てきた家族も
みんなで協力して問題を解決し
とても平和な雰囲気を
つくり出していました
and create a very peaceful family life.
It was really beautiful to see how far
聖書の原則を当てはめて
より良い家族になる様子は
they had come by applying Bible principles.
美しかったですね
In review, this symposium has taught us
まとめです このシンポジウムで
聖書の原則が家庭の平和に欠かせない
that Bible principles can be used
地図のようなもので
あることを学びました
as a road map to family peace.
Work hard to show love and respect,
これからも愛と敬意を示し
良いコミュニケーションを取り
to improve communication,
to work together as a team,
みんなで協力し 一緒に
エホバに仕えていきましょう
and to worship Jehovah together.
And please be patient with one another
家族の中でお互いに辛抱し
平和に役立つ習慣を身に付けてください
as you form habits that lead to peace.
With Jehovah’s help, you and your family
エホバの助けで 皆さんの家族も
will enjoy peace that only he can provide.
エホバだけが与えられる
平和を味わえるでしょう
ありがとうございました
兄弟たちの話から
Thank you, brothers.
We benefited from thinking
about how we can apply
聖書の教えを
当てはめる大切さを学べました
the Bible principles you shared
and from the practical lessons
in the dramatizations.
ビデオからも とても役立つ教訓を
得ることができました
私たちは世界が平和になることを
願っています
All of us long to see true peace on earth.
平和はどう実現するのでしょうか
How will that be accomplished?
And how can we prove
that we honor and support
私たちは王であるイエス･キリストを
支持していることを
Jehovah’s appointed King, Christ Jesus?
どのように示せるでしょうか
Let’s listen as Brother Mark Noumair,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
教育委員会の援助者
マーク･ヌマール兄弟が
次の話で そうした点について
話してくださいます
provides these answers and more in the talk,
主題は
「『平和の統治者』を心から支持する」
“Loyally Support the ‘Prince of Peace.’”
想像してください
Imagine the scene: It’s nighttime.
今は夜です
You’re in the garden of Gethsemane
with your close friends and beloved Teacher.
あなたはイエスや他の使徒たちと
一緒にゲッセマネの庭園にいます
Suddenly, you hear a crowd coming.
突然 大勢の人が来ます
They’re being led by a man you know,
Judas Iscariot.
先頭にいるのはユダ・イスカリオテです
ユダはイエスに近づいて
頬に口づけします
He approaches Jesus
and kisses him on the cheek.
He then steps aside
as men move in to arrest Jesus.
すると 人々が進み出て
イエスを捕らえます
Your emotions churn inside you.
あなたは気が動転します
Your Master and Lord is being arrested
—the Son of God.
主であり神の子である
イエスが捕らえられました
How can this be happening?
「何ということだ どうしよう」
What do you do?
Before you can even decide what to do,
あなたの考えがまとまらないうちに
Peter draws his sword
ペテロが剣を抜いて大祭司の
奴隷の耳を切り落とします
and chops off the ear
of the slave of the high priest.
するとイエスがこう言います
Then Jesus says to Peter:
“Return your sword to its place,
「その剣をさやに収めなさい
for all those who take up the sword
will perish by the sword.”
剣を取る人は皆 剣で滅びます」
それからイエスは 奇跡によって
大祭司の奴隷の耳を癒やします
And then you watch the unbelievable,
as Jesus heals the man’s ear.
ペテロは 神の子のために戦うのは
高潔なことだと思ったのでしょう
Peter must have thought
that it was a great and noble thing
to fight on behalf of the Son of God.
でもイエスはそう思いませんでした
But Jesus didn’t think so.
With six words
何と言ったでしょうか
「その剣をさやに収めなさい」です
—“return your sword to its place”—
Jesus taught his disciples
an important lesson.
弟子たちに何を
教えたかったのでしょうか
彼らは戦うべきではなく
This was not their fight;
戦う時でもないということです
nor was it the time to fight.
So in this talk,
この話の中では
we’re going to focus our attention
on an insidious way
私たちもペテロのようになってしまう
ことがあり得る ということについて
that any of us, like Peter,
考えたいと思います
can become inadvertently involved
in this world’s conflicts
気付かないうちに世の中の問題に
巻き込まれてしまうことが
あり得る ということです
without even realizing it.
And we will talk about how we
can avoid making that serious mistake.
どうすればそのようなことを
避けられるかについて考えましょう
But first,
でもまず イエスが捕らえられた
時のことをもう少し考えてみましょう
let’s discuss why Jesus
did not ask his Father
どうして父に「12軍団⋯⋯の天使」
を送ってもらわなかったのでしょうか
to send “12 legions of angels”
to help him when being arrested.
そのことにはイエスの名が
関係しています
It has to do with Jesus’ name.
So please open your Bible
to Isaiah chapter 9,
では聖書を開いて ご一緒に
イザヤ 9:6を読んでみましょう
and let’s read verse 6
—Isaiah 9:6.
イザヤ 9章の6節を開きましょう
Now, we know Jesus has many titles,
イエスにはたくさんの称号がありますが
but in this verse,
we’re going to focus on just one.
そのうちの1つに注目したいと思います
Verse 6:
6節
“For a child has been born to us,
「私たちのために子が生まれた
私たちに男子が与えられた
“a son has been given to us;
“and the rulership will rest on his shoulder.
彼は肩に統治の責任を負い
“His name will be called Wonderful Counselor,
素晴らしい助言者 力強い神 永遠の父
“Mighty God, Eternal Father,
平和の統治者と呼ばれる」
Prince of Peace.”
Why is Jesus called “Prince of Peace”?
イエスはどうして「平和の統治者」
なのでしょうか
イエスが生まれた時に
Well, consider what Jehovah’s angel
declared to the shepherds in the field
天使たちが羊飼いたちに何と言ったか
思い起こしてみましょう
at Jesus’ birth at Luke 2:14.
ルカ 2:14でこのように
言っています
They said:
“Glory in the heights above to God,
「［天］では神に栄光が 地上では
神に喜ばれる人々の間に
and on earth peace among men of goodwill.”
平和がありますように」
How appropriate for the angels to announce
天使たちは 平和の統治者
となる方が生まれた時に
that at the birth
of the destined Prince of Peace,
神に喜ばれる人々は神から
平和を与えられると宣言したのです
there would be divine peace
for those who have God’s goodwill!
But when will this become a reality?
いつ与えられるのでしょうか
It didn’t happen when Jesus was on earth,
イエスが地上にいた間は平和ではなく
and we certainly don’t see peace today.
現在も平和とは言えません
今はどんな状態でしょうか
Instead of peace, what do we see?
We see the nations that are locked
in hostilities and aggression
国々は他の国より優勢になろうと
いがみ合ったり争ったりしています
in a competition for world dominance.
世界中で暴力がはびこっています
We see global violence and bloodshed.
But please don’t lose heart.
でも どうかがっかりしないでください
Because we don’t see peace now
does not mean it’s not coming.
今平和じゃないとしても
必ず平和になるからです
Isaiah 9:6
イザヤ 9:6の言葉は
単なる希望的観測ではありません
—it’s not just wishful thinking.
It’s a promise from Almighty God,
and Jehovah cannot lie.
それは神の約束であり
エホバは偽ることができません
All his prophecies come true.
エホバの預言は全て実現します
In fact,
let’s read the last portion of verse 7
その点で イザヤ 9:7の
最後の文を読んでみましょう
in Isaiah chapter 9.
The last verse
(the last portion of verse 7) says:
9:7の最後の一文です
こうあります
“The zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.”
「大軍を率いる熱心な神
エホバがそうならせる」
What does that mean?
熱心な神エホバは いいかげんではなく
It means that Jehovah
does nothing in a half-hearted way.
He’s zealous to bring peace, and he will.
確実に平和をもたらします
We can be sure
that whatever Jehovah promises,
エホバが約束したことは必ず
実現すると確信できます
he will fully accomplish.
どうやって平和が
もたらされるのでしょうか
So how will peace come to the earth?
平和の統治者は
何か言っているでしょうか
Did the Prince of Peace give us a clue?
Yes, he did.
言っています 実際
In fact, the key to everlasting peace
イエスが語った永続する
平和の鍵について
is on the lips of millions of people
throughout the world.
現在世界中で大勢の人が伝えています
They know it by heart.
その言葉を読んでみましょう
But let’s read it at Matthew 6:9, 10
マタイ 6章の9, 10節です
—Matthew 6:9.
マタイ 6:9
What a beautiful thought for us!
ここには素晴らしいことが
書かれています
This is how everlasting peace
is going to come through.
この言葉が実現することによって
It depends on the fulfillment
of these verses.
永続する平和が
もたらされることになります
Verse 9:
9節 「このように
祈らなければなりません
“You must pray, then, this way:
‘Our Father in the heavens,
『天におられる私たちの父よ
let your name [the name Jehovah]
be sanctified.’”
［エホバという］お名前が
神聖なものとされますように』」
The emphasis that we place
on the name of God
神のお名前は重要であり
単に知っているというだけでは
不十分です
is not merely a matter
of religious knowledge.
全ての人が 神の清いお名前に
敬意を示す必要があります
Everyone must know God’s name
and treat it as something holy and respected.
It has to be something sacred.
神聖な名前だからです
傷つけられた名誉が
回復されなければなりません
It must be cleared of all the reproach
that has been heaped upon it.
地球全体が平和になって
In fact, the well-being
of the entire universe and its inhabitants
全ての人が幸せに暮らすには
depends upon the sanctification
of Jehovah’s name.
エホバのお名前が神聖なもの
とされる必要があるのです
では10節を見ましょう
Now, let’s look at verse 10:
“Let your Kingdom come.
「あなたの王国が来ますように
あなたの望まれることが
Let your will take place,
as in heaven, also on earth.”
天と同じように地上でも
行われますように」
God’s Kingdom
—two words but so important.
この聖句で注目したいのは
神の王国です
神の王国の政府は
God’s Kingdom
is the most powerful government
ほかのどんな政府よりも
はるかに力があります
humanity will ever see.
There is no nation or empire
どんな国や勢力も
that can withstand
the might of God’s Kingdom.
神の王国に逆らって
立つことなどできません
And any nation who thinks
they can block the coming of God’s Kingdom
神の王国が来るのを
止められると考える国は
あたかもアリのようです
is like an ant who plants itself firmly
on the railroad track
小さなアリが線路の上で
向かってくる列車の前に立ちはだかり
and with his hand raised defiantly
shouts to the oncoming locomotive:
手を上げてこう言っているかのようです
「止まれ！ ここから先は行かせない」
“Stop! You can’t run over me.”
Well, God’s heavenly government has the power
エホバにとって人間の
政府はアリのようで
to destroy all present-day violent regimes.
神の王国はそれらの政府を
簡単に滅ぼせます
They’re like ants to Jehovah.
And he will eliminate their ability
人間の政府が戦争をしたり
争い合ったりすることは
to wage war, to foment conflict,
and to shed blood.
二度となくなります
マタイ 6:9, 10には
So, yes, Matthew 6:9, 10
—it’s that valuable and important
for lasting peace.
確かに平和の鍵が示されています
God’s Kingdom is the only road
to lasting peace.
神の王国が 永続する
平和をもたらすのです
その王国の王であるイエス・キリストは
And in his role as King,
啓示 19:15にあるように
Revelation 19:15 describes Jesus
剣で国々を討ち 「鉄のつえをもって
人々を処罰し」ます
as ‘striking the nations with an iron rod.’
Soon, Jehovah will give
the command to his Son,
間もなくイエスは エホバに命じられて
平和を乱している全てのものを
滅ぼすのです
and he will destroy
all the things that disrupt peace.
Gone will be the terror
that we have grown accustomed to living with
今私たちが毎日のように
感じている恐れは
day in and day out.
過去のものとなります
その後どうなるでしょうか
So, what will happen next?
聖書を見てみましょう
This is what will happen
—Psalm 37:10, 11.
ご一緒に詩編 37:10, 11を
開いて 読んでみましょう
Let’s open our Bibles here
to Psalm 37:10, 11,
and just allow this prophecy to absorb
この聖句を読むと将来が楽しみになり
and to thrill our minds and our hearts
期待で胸が躍ることでしょう
and give us a hope for the future.
読みます
詩編 37:10
Verse 10 of Psalm 37:
“Just a little while longer,
「ほんのもう少しすれば
“and the wicked will be no more
[a little while longer];
悪人はいなくなる
［ほんのもう少しすれば］
you will look at where they were,
and they will not be there.”
彼らがいた場所を見ても もういない」
“Just a little while longer.”
家族旅行で子供たちが親に
It’s just like children saying
to their parents
「まだ着かないの？」と
尋ねることがあります
when going on a trip
“Are we there yet?”
親は「もう少しだよ」と言います
and the parents say
“Just a little while longer.”
すると子供は安心します
And that brings comfort to them,
and it’s the same with us.
私たちも同じです
考えてください
So imagine that!
あともう少しで どこに行っても
悪い人を見掛けることはなくなります
This means you go into the streets,
you’re looking for a wicked person,
and you will not be able to find even one.
「ほんのもう少しすれば
悪人はいなくなる」のです
“The wicked will be no more.”
そしてどうなるでしょうか
“But the meek will possess the earth.”
That’s what we’re speaking about in verse 11.
11節に書かれていることを
読みましょう
Let’s read that:
“But the meek will possess the earth,
「しかし 温厚な人は地上に住み続け
and they will find exquisite delight
in the abundance of peace.”
豊かな平和をこの上なく喜ぶ」
素晴らしいですね
We love reading that.
豊かな平和です
Men will be at peace.
They will be at peace with themselves,
with their neighbors, with their God.
他の人とも神とも いつも平和な
関係でいられるようになったら
How does that sound to you?
どんなにいいでしょう
Meditate on that.
新しい世界のことを
じっくり考えてみてください
Can you see yourself there
in a peaceful new world
where the only news to tune into
ニュースといえば 今日誰が
復活してくるかとか
is regarding who’s getting resurrected today
あなたは誰を教えるかといった
平和なものばかりです
or which new person you will be assigned
to teach about Jehovah?
Can you imagine the joy
of studying with a person,
どんな人を教えることになるか
想像してください
not just from a different culture,
文化や時代が全く違う人かもしれません
but from a different time period,
seeing things through their eyes
その人が真理を学んで
あなたのようにエホバを
愛するようになります
as they come to love Jehovah as you do?
間もなく 平和の統治者が
Well, soon the Prince of Peace
will turn this world
into one of sheer delight
世界を喜びでいっぱいにします
—no more borders,
no more threats, no more worries—
国境はなく 恐れや心配もなくなり
全ての人が豊かな平和を
楽しめるようになります
just an abundance of peace
with your brothers and sisters.
Do you want to be there?
楽しみですか
私もです
Me too.
So how can we show our loyal support
for the Prince of Peace?
では 世界を変える平和の統治者を
心から支持しましょう
Please watch the following video,
支持していることを
今どのように示せるか
and notice the different ways
we can do this right now.
次のビデオを見ながら考えましょう
“I am no part of the world.”
「彼らも世の人々のようではない」
But is the world a part of me?
私はどうだろうか
I’m pressured every day
自分たちの権利のために
闘わなければならないという
プレッシャーを
to get involved in political issues
that affect me socially,
いつも感じています
. . . environmentally,
環境問題についても
. . . and economically.
経済についてもです
That pressure could rob me
of my peace of mind
そういう圧がかかると
心がざわざわします
. . . and influence how I think.
自分の考え方も影響を受け
I could take sides in my heart,
心の中で政治を批判したくなります
even if I’m not aware of it.
But I know that Jehovah
でも 人間が抱える問題全てを
正してくれるのはエホバです
will care for all of mankind’s concerns
. . . by means of his Kingdom
イエス・キリストを王とする
神の王国によって正してくださいます
ruled by his Son, Jesus Christ.
I show my support for him
in my prayers,
私はイエスを支持しています
祈る事柄によっても
. . . in how I think and feel,
どんな考え方をするかという点でも
. . . and by teaching others
神の王国が何をしてくれるかを
知らせることによってもです
what the Kingdom will do for mankind.
I know there are millions
世界中に大勢の兄弟姉妹がいます
of brothers and sisters
all over the world
. . . who loyally support
the “Prince of Peace”
みんな「平和の統治者」を
心から支持しています
just like me, because I
私は
. . . I
. . . I am no part of the world.
私は世の人々のようではないからです
あなたの国ではどんなことが
問題になっていますか
So, what takes away the peace
in the country where you live?
身近でどんなことが
話題になっていますか
in your community?
in your town? in your society?
Most likely,
it’s the hot-button social issues.
人々の意見が割れている
問題があることでしょう
Did you notice
how our two brothers and sister
ビデオの兄弟姉妹は どのように
平和の統治者を支持していたでしょうか
showed their loyal support
for the Prince of Peace?
どんな問題がありましたか
What issues affected them?
Unfair tax hikes, blatant injustice,
a disregard of the environment
不当な増税 あからさまな不公正
環境汚染などです
どれも すぐに取り組むべき重大な
問題に思えるかもしれません
—all things in themselves seemed
like noble causes worthy to get involved.
‘How can they get away with this?
「どうしてこんなことが起きているのか
It’s not right.
We should do something.’
これはどうにかしないといけない」
そう思うでしょうか
Does that sound familiar?
We may not have a literal sword in our hand,
手に文字通りの剣を持っていなくても
ペテロのように行動
したくなるでしょうか
but we all have our Peterlike moments.
And if we’re not careful,
issues that are close to our heart
気を付けていないと
感情的になってしまって
エホバの観点で物事を見られなく
なってしまうかもしれません
can charge our emotions
and we can lose our spiritual balance.
So, what can help us
when we see things that are wrong?
では 問題に直面したら
どうすればいいでしょうか
Remember what the Prince of Peace
said to Peter
平和の統治者がペテロに
何と言ったか思い起こしてください
in that highly charged moment:
「その剣をさやに収めなさい」
“Return your sword to its place.”
あなたは戦うべきではない
ということです
In other words, this is not your fight.
では何をしますか
戦うよりもずっといいことをします
So, what do we do?
We do something far better than fight.
伝道です 王国の
良い知らせを伝えるたびに
We preach.
Each time that we share the Kingdom news,
イエスの統治を
支持していることを示せます
we proclaim our support for Jesus’ rule.
注意点として
But here’s the thing:
王国の良い知らせを
伝えたいと思っているなら
If we truly believe
in the good news of the Kingdom,
その妨げになるような言動は
避けなければなりません
we will not do anything
that hinders our ability to tell it.
Once again, it’s so important
大切なので もう一度言います
that if we truly believe
in the good news of the Kingdom,
王国の良い知らせを
伝えたいと思っているなら
その妨げになるような言動は
避けなければなりません
we will not do anything
that hinders our ability to tell it.
なぜでしょうか ペテロ自身が書いた
言葉を読んで 考えてみましょう
Why?
Well, let’s find out.
Let’s open up to Peter’s words himself
at 1 Peter 2:12
ペテロ第一 2章の12節です
—1 Peter 2:12.
ペテロはここで 私たちが
いつも立派に行動する必要がある
理由について説明しています
Peter helps us here with why we need
to maintain our conduct properly.
ペテロ第一 2:12
First Peter 2:12:
「世の人々の中でいつも
立派に行動してください
“Maintain your conduct fine
among the nations,
“so that when they accuse you
of being wrongdoers,
そうすれば人々は 皆さんのことを
悪人だと非難していても
“they may be eyewitnesses
of your fine works
皆さんの立派な行動を見て
and, as a result,
glorify God in the day of his inspection.”
検分の日に神を
たたえるようになるでしょう」
ペテロもこのことを学びました
So Peter had to learn this.
But do we see the connection?
何が分かりますか
私たちの言動はエホバの
評判に影響します
Our actions and words
are directly linked to Jehovah.
When people see us,
they see a people that worships Jehovah.
人々は私たちを見て
エホバの証人が何をするか
また 何を話すか といったことに
よく注目しています
And when people hear us,
they hear a people that worships Jehovah.
Imagine how our freeness of speech
to speak about God’s Kingdom
例えば 政治問題でどちらかの側を
支持するような発言をするなら
would be hindered if we were to voice
a position for a political issue!
神の王国について
話しにくくなってしまいます
And it can happen so easily.
注意していないと
It can happen at work, at school,
with relatives, and so forth.
職場などで政治的な発言を
してしまうかもしれません
Satan sets the trap masterfully.
サタンは私たちをわなに
掛けようとして いつも狙っています
He’s just waiting.
私たちが憤りを感じるようなことで
If he could only make us
“chop off the ear” of anything in this world
誰かの“耳を切り落とす”ような
行動を取らせようとしています
that causes hurt and indignation in our heart
or if he can hook our heartstrings
by getting us emotionally charged,
私たちを感情的にならせて
世の中の問題に巻き込み
世の人々のように
ならせようとしています
he can then step back and reel us in.
本当の平和をもたらすのは
神だということを
The new world, our hope for true peace,
all starts to fade into the background.
見失わせようとしているのです
Don’t give him that chance!
惑わされないようにしましょう
Be determined to do
いつもテトス 3:1, 2に書かれて
いるような行動を取れるように
what Titus 3:1, 2 tells us.
決意していたいと思います
Let’s read that
—Titus chapter 3,
テトス 3章の1, 2節です
verses 1 and 2.
Here is the Scriptural admonition:
ここをご一緒に読んでみましょう
“Continue reminding them to be in subjection
「引き続き兄弟たちに次の事柄を
思い起こさせてください
“and to be obedient
to governments and authorities,
政府や権威者に従うこと
あらゆる良い活動のために
用意をすること
“to be ready for every good work,
“to speak injuriously of no one,
not to be quarrelsome,
誰のことも悪く言わず
争いを好まず 分別を働かせ
but to be reasonable,
displaying all mildness toward all men.”
誰に対してもいつも
温和に接することです」
‘Be in subjection
この中で 「政府や権威者に
従う」ようにと言われています
and be obedient
to governments and authorities.’
Well, now let’s break that down.
従うために私たちは
どうすればよいのでしょうか
In practical terms, what does it mean?
It means to obey the laws of the land
and pay taxes,
法律を守り きちんと税金を納めます
to not speak negatively
about the superior authorities,
上位の権威のことを
悪く言ったりはしません
and to be careful not to take sides
on political issues
心の中でも 政治問題で
どちらかの側を支持したりしません
(not even in our hearts).
Do you remember
that expression from the video?
ビデオを思い起こしてみましょう
世の人々のようではない
ということが強調されていました
“I am no part of the world.
But is the world a part of me?”
Of course,
when we find ourselves
では カエサルの法律が神の律法に
反している場合はどうでしょうか
between Caesar’s law and God’s law,
we know what to do.
We apply Acts 5:29
and “obey God as ruler rather than men.”
使徒 5:29にある通り
「人ではなく神に
従わなければなりません」
We know that.
そして たとえ不公正や
ひどい事柄を目にしても
But like Jesus, who healed the ear
of the armed guard Malchus,
we’re determined to react with mildness
奴隷マルコスの耳を
癒やしたイエスのように
when provoked by an injustice
or cruelty in this world.
いつも温和な態度を
示せるよう努力しましょう
In conclusion,
結論として 私たちには平和の統治者を
支持する素晴らしい機会があります
we have the indescribable privilege
to honor the Prince of Peace.
And how reassuring it is to know
that Jesus understands our feelings!
そして うれしいことに
イエスは私たちの感情や気持ちを
理解してくれています
He understands our emotions
when we see things that we know are wrong.
何か間違ったことを目にした時に
つらい気持ちになることを知っています
He knows these things hurt our heart.
何とかしたいという気持ちです
We just want to make things right.
But remember the critical lesson
でも イエスがゲッセマネの庭園で
教えた大切なことを思い起こしましょう
he taught his apostles
in the garden of Gethsemane:
あなたは戦うべきではない
ということです
This is not your fight.
Rather, Jehovah, the King of Eternity,
and Jesus, the Prince of Peace,
永遠の王エホバと平和の統治者イエスは
私たちにこう言っています
are telling us:
“This is our fight. Leave it in our hands.”
「私たちが戦います
任せておきなさい」
もう間もなく イザヤ 9:6, 7の
預言は完全に実現することになります
Soon, the prophecy at Isaiah 9:6, 7
will be fulfilled completely.
In the meantime,
keep preaching about the Kingdom.
その時まで王国について
伝え続けましょう
Avoid saying or doing anything
政治問題でどちらかの側を支持して
いるかのような言動は避けましょう
that suggests taking sides
on a political issue.
Don’t allow yourself to “chop off the ear”
たとえ問題に直面しても
誰かの“耳を切り落とす”ような
行動を取ってはなりません
of the injustices and the causes of conflict
of this old world.
Peter tried that, but it didn’t work.
ペテロはそうして 失敗しました
あの晩 大切な教訓を学び
He learned a big lesson
that day in the garden,
決して忘れませんでした
and he never forgot it.
私たちも忘れないようにしましょう
May we never forget it either.
Now is the time to show
your active and loyal support
今こそ平和の統治者イエスを
心から支持するべき時です
for the Prince of Peace
ペテロ第二 3:14で
ペテロが勧めているように
as we echo Peter’s words at 2 Peter 3:14
「最終的に汚点も傷もない平和な人と
and “do [our] utmost to be found finally
by [Jehovah and the Prince of Peace]
［エホバと平和の統治者］に
認めていただけるよう
spotless and unblemished and in peace.”
最善を尽くし」ましょう
王国の王であるイエス･キリストを
Thank you, Brother Noumair,
for strengthening our determination
心から支持したいという
決意が強まりました
to give our undivided support
to God’s appointed King, Christ Jesus.
ヌマール兄弟 ありがとうございました
This brings us
to the final talk of today’s session.
では 今日の最後の話を聞きましょう
イエスは弟子たちに
平和を与えると約束しました
Jesus promised to give his followers peace.
Why is the peace that Jesus gives
far superior
イエスが与える平和が
世の中で考えられている平和より
はるかに勝っているのは
どうしてでしょうか
to any peace that this world promises?
And how can we safeguard the gift of peace
イエスが与えてくださった平和を大切に
するにはどうしたらいいでしょうか
that Jesus has given us?
Please follow along
as Brother Anthony Morris,
統治体のアンソニー･モリス兄弟の
話を注意深く聞きましょう
a member of the Governing Body,
話の主題は 「偽物の平和に
惑わされないでください」です
delivers the talk,
“Do Not Be Misled by Imitation Peace!”
Jesus taught us that Satan
イエスは私たちに サタンが
「うその根源」だと教えています
is “the father of the lie.”
サタンは完全な女性エバをだましました
We recall that he deceived Eve,
a perfect woman.
私たちが愛するエホバについて
うそをついたのです
He lied about our precious Jehovah.
Now, you’re familiar (many of you)
with Revelation chapter 12.
皆さんの多くは啓示 12章の聖句を
よくご存じと思います
I invite you to find that
見てみましょう
—Revelation chapter 12.
啓示 12章です
12:7, 8には
And in this chapter, verses 7 and 8,
「天で戦争が起こった」ことが
書かれています
it addressed the fact
that “war broke out in heaven.”
But notice
そして9節には
that after he’s kicked out of heaven,
サタンがどうなったかが書かれています
in verse 9 we read:
「こうして 大きな竜は投げ落とされた
“So down the great dragon was hurled,
“the original serpent,
the one called Devil and Satan,
あの初めの蛇で 悪魔サタンと呼ばれ
“who is misleading
the entire inhabited earth;
全世界を惑わしている者である
“he was hurled down to the earth,
and his angels
彼は地に投げ落とされ
邪悪な天使たちも共に投げ落とされた」
were hurled down with him.”
サタンが何をしているかが
Now, I read it that way specifically,
はっきり分かります
but what it doesn’t say is
今読んだ9節の中ほどには
(in the middle part of verse 9):
何と書かれていたでしょうか
サタンが 「全世界を
“Satan, who is [trying to mislead]
［惑わそうとしている］」とは
書かれていません
the entire inhabited earth.”
そうではなく サタンが
No, he “is{
「全世界を惑わしている」と
書かれています
the entire inhabited earth.”
That’s crucial to understand
when we think about the theme of this talk,
この話の主題は「偽物の平和に
惑わされないでください」です
not to be misled by imitation peace,
私たちは 世の支配者であるサタンが
because as “the ruler of the world,”
世界を惑わしているということを
理解しておく必要があります
that’s what he’s out to do—mislead.
コリント第二 11章には
In fact, it’s an interesting point
here in 2 Corinthians chapter 11
興味深いことが書かれています
サタンがどのように
to appreciate
how he goes about misleading,
or at least it’s addressed here
人々を惑わしているのかを知る上で
助けになります
to serve as a good warning for us.
心に留めておきたい点です
And an interesting point with the revision
改訂版の「新世界訳」では
以前とは違う表現が使われています
of the New World Translation
改訂前の聖書を使っていた皆さんは
(for those of you in the truth before 2013
その違いに気付いているかもしれません
when it was revised, you’ll remember this)
コリント第二 11:14です
in verse 14 of 2 Corinthians chapter 11:
“And no wonder,
for Satan himself keeps disguising himself
「それも不思議ではありません
サタンが光の使いに
成り済ましているからです」
as an angel of light.”
Now, the New World Translation
今はこういう表現ですが
used to say before the revision
改訂前は 「サタン自身が自分を⋯⋯
“[transforms] himself
into an angel of light.”
光の使いに変様させている」と
なっていました
この「変様」に当たるギリシャ語には
Well, the very English word “metamorphosis,”
like for a caterpillar transforming
into a beautiful butterfly,
幼虫が美しいチョウに変わる
という意味があります
that’s where it comes from,
the Greek language.
「変様」という語はそこから来ています
でも改訂訳では「変様」という語は
And that word was not in verse 14.
使われていません
No, because Satan can’t transform himself
実際 サタンは「光の使い」に
なることはできません
into “an angel of light”
(so it’s an improved translation),
むしろ改訂版にある通り
「成り済まして」いるのです
but he does disguise.
He’s a masquerader.
偽物にすぎません
平和についても
偽物をつくり出しています
And he does that with the subject of peace.
His world offers a sort of peace,
サタンの支配する世界が約束する平和は
but it’s imitation peace.
偽物の平和です
ではイエスが与えると約束した平和は
どういうものでしょうか
Now, Jesus is distinguished,
though, with the peace that he gives.
And if you’ll follow along here
ご一緒に見てみましょう
in John chapter 14,
ヨハネ 14章です
he himself explains it to us.
イエス自身が説明しています
And we treasure the Gospel accounts,
とても励みになる言葉です
verse 27: “I leave you peace;
27節 「私はあなたたちが受けている
平和をこれからも与えます
“I give you my peace.
それは世が与える平和とは違います
“I do not give it to you
the way the world gives it.
Do not let your hearts be troubled
nor let them shrink out of fear.”
動揺してはならず
弱気になってもなりません」
So Jesus gives us his peace, see.
イエスは平和を与えると言っています
イエスが与えてくれる平和というのは
And the peace that Jesus gives us,
真理を知った時に得られる
心の穏やかさのことです
it’s this inner calm once you know
the truth and Jesus gives us the peace.
イエスに愛され エホバに
愛されていることを実感できるので
We have this confidence that he loves us
and Jehovah loves us,
イエスとエホバとの良い関係
so that we enjoy a good,
peaceful relationship with them
平和な関係を楽しむことができ
and a good conscience.
健全な良心を持てます
And we look forward to the Kingdom
removing all war and death.
そして王国によって戦争や死が
なくなる時を心待ちにしています
Now, a point to make here:
ここで注目したい点があります
Satan wants us to trade
サタンはイエスが与える平和ではなく
the peace that Jesus gives
自分が与える平和が本物だと
信じ込ませようとしています
for his imitation peace
その平和について
世界中で宣伝しています
that he has advertised in the world.
Now, in this talk,
この話では
サタンが宣伝している
偽物の平和を3つ取り上げ
we will consider
three forms of imitation peace
and why the peace
that Jesus gives is superior.
イエスが与える平和が
なぜ優れているといえるのかを考えます
1つ目に お金や物がたくさんあっても
The first one has to do with material things
—how they’ll not bring true peace.
本当の平和を得られない
ということを考えます
And to help us with that,
turn to Matthew chapter 4,
この点について
マタイ 4章を見てみましょう
この章は
and we’ll be referring to this chapter
「偽物の平和に惑わされないで
ください」というこの話の中で
throughout this particular talk
about not being misled by imitation peace.
何度も取り上げられます
イエスが教えたことから
お金や物がたくさんあっても
And this one
is connected with material things
—how they don’t bring true peace—
本当の平和は
得られないことが分かります
in the example Jesus sets forth here.
So in Matthew chapter 4:
マタイ 4:1からです
“Then Jesus was led by the spirit
「それからイエスは
聖なる力に導かれて荒野に行き
“up into the wilderness
to be tempted by the Devil.
悪魔から誘惑を受けた
“After he had fasted
for 40 days and 40 nights,
40日間ずっと断食した後
空腹を感じた
“he felt hungry.
“And the Tempter approached and said to him:
誘惑者がイエスに近づき 言った
“‘If you are a son of God,
『神の子なら これらの石に
パンになるように命じなさい』
tell these stones to become loaves of bread.’
“But he answered: ‘It is written:
イエスは答えた
『「人は パンだけではなく
“‘“Man must live, not on bread alone,
エホバの口から出る全ての言葉によって
but on every word that comes
from Jehovah’s mouth.”’”
生きなければならない」と
書いてあります』」
Isn’t that a beautiful rebuttal?
見事な答えではないでしょうか
See, Jesus refused to trade
イエスは非常に空腹でしたが
his peace for material things
(in this case, bread),
物 この場合パンと引き換えに
本当の平和を手放すことは
ありませんでした
even though he was hungry.
So serving Jehovah was more important to him
イエスにとっては 物よりもエホバに
仕えることの方が大切だったのです
than material things, see.
世の中では多くの人が定年後
安心して暮らすには
In the world, they have this thinking,
‘Well, you need
お金がどれだけ必要かと
いったことを考えています
a certain amount of money to retire,’
お金や物のことで頭がいっぱいです
and they’re constantly
focused on material things
でもイエスは
そうではありませんでした
—not Jesus, see.
It’s superior peace from Jehovah God.
神の平和の方が優れていることを
知っていたのです
So it’s only temporary anyway,
人々は一生の間ずっと
お金や物を得ようとします
the material benefits that people seek
でもそこから得られる喜びは
一時的なものにすぎません
and pursue throughout their lives.
しかし 私たちは
本当の喜びを味わえます
Now we can enjoy true contentment
because Jehovah God is going to care for us.
エホバ神が世話してくれるからです
We know that many have
personal experiences to prove that.
多くの兄弟姉妹は
そのことを実際に経験しています
Now, in the following video,
次のビデオをご覧ください
see what a brother learned
about the so-called peace
ある兄弟はお金や物ではなく
エホバを第一にすることの
大切さを学びました
that the world promises.
As a family, we were doing
very well spiritually.
私たちの家族はよくやっていました
家族の崇拝もし 伝道に行き
We did family worship, went preaching,
and went to the meetings together.
集会に一緒に行っていました
After some time, we began
そのうち 生活が苦しくなりました
to encounter financial problems.
その日の食べ物を
買えないこともありました
At times, we did not even have money
to buy food
for each day.
この辺りの人たちは
たいてい家族を養うために
Many people in our area
were going to South Africa
to provide basic needs for their families.
南アフリカに出稼ぎに行っていました
So I decided to go as well,
私もそうしました
leaving behind my wife
to take care of our seven children.
妻に7人の子供の世話を任せてです
This affected me spiritually
南アフリカでは言葉が
分からず 苦労しました
because I did not know the language,
I was unable to preach,
伝道できず 集会に行っても
理解できませんでした
and I did not benefit from the meetings.
家族から遠く離れていたので
Being so far from my family
caused me to neglect
my responsibility as a family head.
家族の頭としてやるべきことが
できていませんでした
As a result, my family grew weak spiritually
そのため家族の信仰が弱くなり
みんなが寂しい思いをしました
and we all missed each other very much.
出稼ぎに行ったのは
間違いだったと気付きました
I realized that I had made
a wrong decision going abroad.
My conscience started to trouble me greatly.
ひどく心が痛んでつらくなりました
Then I remembered the example of Baruch
エレミヤ 45:5にある
found at Jeremiah 45:5.
バルクのことを思い出しました
バルクも私と同じで
Baruch may have wanted
to pursue material riches as I had.
いい生活をしたかったのかもしれない
でも 諭されて考え直しました
When he was helped, he returned.
それで私も物やお金ではなく
I decided then to put Jehovah in first place
エホバを第一にすることにしました
instead of searching for material things.
家に帰って家族が元気に
エホバに仕えられるよう
So I started to make changes to go home
and help my family spiritually.
助けようと心に決めました
南アフリカを離れ
マラウイに戻ってきました
When I left South Africa
and reached the border of Malawi
(after leaving my family
for about six months),
家族と会うのは6カ月ぶりでした
I felt great happiness in my heart,
本当にほっとしました
and I am still happy till now.
今の方がずっと幸せです
Studying the Bible has helped me.
聖書を学ぶことが役立っています
We still encounter financial problems,
今も生活は厳しいですが
サタンが支配する世界にいる限り
but I remember that in Satan’s world,
there is nowhere we can go
and have no problems.
問題がなくなることはありません
Now I serve as an elder.
今 長老として奉仕しています
My family is progressing spiritually.
家族も元気にエホバに仕えています
And this makes me very happy,
エホバとの絆が強まったので
because my relationship
with Jehovah is strong.
今とても幸せです
つらい経験を通して
大切なことを学びました
Yes, he learned a hard lesson.
He goes to South Africa
南アフリカに行きましたが
集会に行っても理解できず
—meetings interrupted and no field service.
伝道もできませんでした
And then he remembers Baruch,
そしてバルクのことを思い出しました
secretary for Jeremiah.
エレミヤの秘書官です
兄弟は家族のもとに戻って
王国を第一にするようになりました
And he returns to be with his family,
putting the Kingdom first,
and we appreciate him
being truthful and sharing that experience.
正直に経験を話してくださったことに
感謝しています
That’s imitation peace,
going after material things.
確かに お金や物からは
本物の平和は得られません
Now this next one, it’s quite interesting.
次にお話しするのも
非常に大切なことです
So pay close attention
ですから よく聞いてください
because there may be some
listening who need this counsel.
このアドバイスに従うことは
とても大切です
Satan’s world says that we
サタンはこう言います
「心の平和を得るには
聖書の基準を無視しても構わない
can ignore Bible standards
and that we might need
to ignore some of them to gain peace of mind.
時にはそうすることが必要だ」
Here are two examples
that we’re going to analyze in this talk.
これから2つの例を
取り上げたいと思います
A person may reason
that marrying an unbeliever
クリスチャンではない人と
結婚することと
or obtaining an unscriptural divorce
聖書に基づく根拠がないのに
will make life easier.
離婚することです
こんなふうに考える人が
いるかもしれません
And they start reasoning this way,
‘I just want to get married,
「私はあの人と結婚したい
クリスチャンではないけれど
とてもいい人だ」
and he’s an unbeliever,
but he’s a nice person.’
Things like that go on
with the treacherous heart.
いろいろ理由を挙げて
正当化しようとします
この点を考えるに当たっても
イエスの手本に注目しましょう
Again, we go to the example
of our Lord and Master, Jesus.
マタイ 4:5-7です
We’re going to read verses 5-7 of Matthew 4:
こうあります
「次いで 悪魔は
イエスを聖なる都に連れていき
“Then the Devil took him
along into the holy city,
神殿の最も高い所に立たせて 言った
“and he stationed him
on the battlement of the temple
“and said to him:
『神の子なら 飛び降りなさい
“‘If you are a son of God,
throw yourself down,
“‘for it is written:
「神はあなたのために
天使たちに命令を出す」
“‘“He will give his angels
a command concerning you,”
「天使たちはあなたを手に乗せて運び
“‘and, “They will carry you on their hands,
あなたが石に足をぶつけないように
する」と書いてありますから』
“so that you may not strike
your foot against a stone.”’
“Jesus said to him: ‘Again, it is written:
イエスは言った
『「エホバ神を試してはならない」とも
書いてあります』」
“You must not put Jehovah
your God to the test.”’”
そう言いました
イエスの答えはとても明快でした
See, Jesus made that very clear.
He was going to be obedient to his Father
イエスはサタンの挑発に乗って
エホバを試すようなことは
しませんでした
and wasn’t going to worry about being testy
お父さんエホバにいつも
従っていたのです 従順でした
with such an experience
as the Devil proposed there.
ですから大切なのは 従うことです
So obedience
—Jesus twice (in a moment we’ll read
another one) said: “It is written.”
イエスはここまでで2回
「と書いてあります」と言っています
He sticks with the Scriptures
—Jehovah’s thinking—
聖書 つまりエホバの考えに
しっかり従いました
and he refused to disobey Jehovah.
エホバに逆らったりしませんでした
Now here’s the question,
ここで考えたいことがあります
Why is the peace that Jesus gives
聖書の基準に反する解決策よりも
superior to the pursuit
イエスが与える平和の方が
優れているといえるのはなぜでしょうか
of unscriptural solutions to our problems?
Let that sink in.
もう一度言います
聖書の基準に反する解決策よりも
Why is the peace that Jesus gives
superior to the pursuit
イエスが与える平和の方が
優れているといえるのはなぜでしょうか
of unscriptural solutions to our problems?
For example, marrying an unbeliever
例えば クリスチャンではない人と
結婚するなら
独身の時に感じていた孤独よりも
—that will likely bring
(and it has happened time after time)
ずっと大きな問題を
抱えるようになるでしょう
that person greater pain
than the longing
they felt when they were single.
そういう例はたくさんあります
I’ve personally seen that
私自身 これまで奉仕してきた
さまざまな会衆で
all too many times in various congregations
そういう例をたくさん目にしてきました
that I’ve had the privilege to serve in.
You see, the other one
is an unscriptural divorce.
聖書の基準に反する離婚をする人は
どうなるでしょうか
It often leads to immoral conduct.
不道徳な行いをしてしまったり
It certainly leads to a troubled conscience,
良心の痛みを感じたり
心に傷を負ったりします
emotional damage
and, of course, a loss of privileges.
特別な奉仕の立場も失います
Now, this is very important to keep in mind.
次のことを忘れないでください
It’s true that with two imperfect individuals
不完全な2人が結婚すれば
いろいろ難しい問題を抱えたり
married to each other,
well, there are going to be difficulties
大変な状況を経験したり
することがあります
and there are going to be challenges.
それは確かです
でも性急に離婚していいでしょうか
But stop and think about this:
When you’re having difficulties,
問題にぶつかった時には
don’t forget that marriage
結婚が神聖な取り決めであることを
思い出してください
is a sacred arrangement.
The world totally has forgotten that.
世の中の人たちは
そのことを気に留めません
So Jehovah will strengthen
エホバは問題を乗り越えられるよう
both to make a success.
夫婦を助けてくれます
You have to keep that in mind:
Jehovah will strengthen and help
忘れないでください
エホバは夫婦を助け 支えてくれます
so that you can succeed
because this is his sacred arrangement.
結婚はエホバの
神聖な取り決めだからです
And the Devil has been attacking
the family arrangement
悪魔はこの終わりの時代の間ずっと
家族という取り決めを攻撃しています
all through the last days of this system,
攻撃の手を強めています
and he’s intensifying it
as he gets closer
to being thrown into the abyss.
間もなく底知れぬ深みに
投げ込まれるからです
次のビデオをご覧ください
Now, in the following video,
偽物の平和を得ようとすると
notice the results
of pursuing imitation peace.
どうなるでしょうか
結婚したばかりのころ
予期しない問題がたくさん起きました
Newly married life came with a lot
of unexpected challenges.
You dream about the way
your marriage will go,
すてきな結婚生活を
思い描いていましたが
but then the reality is quite different.
現実は全く違いました
All we ever did was argue,
いつも言い争うか
口をきかないかのどちらかでした
or we wouldn’t speak to one another.
迷惑を掛けたくないと思って
長老たちには全く相談しませんでした
We never ever went to the elders.
We just didn’t want to bother them.
We just felt, you know,
we needed to figure it out ourselves.
自分たちで何とかしようと思いました
We decided that if the house sold,
家が売れたら
別居しよう ということになりました
then we would separate.
The separation wasn’t a good thing,
別居はいい解決策ではありませんでした
because in some respects
it made things worse.
いろんな悪い影響がありました
息子たちに影響が出ました
It did have an impact on the boys.
反抗するようになり
They started acting out.
They got into some trouble
with the police one time.
警察の厄介になったこともありました
And there was a loneliness
because you’ve gotten married,
一度結婚生活を経験していたので
一人になって余計にさみしく感じました
一人を痛感しました
and now you don’t have that,
and you’re by yourself.
And the same old routine
went on where you’re
それに相変わらず 掃除 洗濯
料理 仕事に追われる毎日でした
cooking and cleaning
and doing laundry and working.
胃の調子が悪くなって
毎朝起きるのがとてもつらく
I felt sick to my stomach.
I had a hard time getting up every morning
and facing the world.
でもやることが山ほどありました
At that point, I felt that I needed
そうなって初めて 長老たちの援助が
必要だと気付きました
to have the elders help out a little bit.
I did pray for Jehovah’s help to direct me,
助けを求めてエホバに祈っているのに
なんでエホバは祈りを聞いて
くれないんだろう と思っていました
and I kept wondering
why Jehovah wasn’t really
祈りが聞かれなかったのは
answering my prayers.
But I kind of realize now
that it was because we were separated.
自分たちが別居していたからだと
今になれば分かります
The expectations of the separation
were not at all what I was thinking.
別居しても 期待していたようには
全くなりませんでした
結婚の誓いについて考えました
I reflected on the marriage vows.
One of the things I thought about
会衆にいたある姉妹のことも
考えるきっかけになりました
was a sister in our congregation.
姉妹が結婚したのは
真理を学ぶ前のことでした
She was married to an unbeliever,
and then she learned the truth.
ご主人はとても乱暴な人で
And he was so violent.
姉妹を殴ったり
本や服を燃やしたりするほどでした
He would beat her; he would burn her books;
he would burn her clothes.
子供たちが集会に行くのも
許しませんでした
He did not allow her children
to attend the meetings.
And I thought about the problems
that Darrel and I had.
「うちはそこまでではない」と
思いました
ダレルは親切だし
そんなことはしませんでした
And I thought:
‘Well, Darrel is a kind person.
He’s never done that.’
And I thought:
こう思いました
「本当に何か手を打たないと
‘You know, this is something
‘that we need to really work on.
‘We need to really put forth the effort
エホバに喜ばれる結婚生活を
送るためには
生活の中でエホバのことを一番に考えて
‘to start applying Bible principles
‘to put Jehovah first in our life
聖書の教えの通りにもっと真剣に
努力しなきゃいけないんだわ」
so that we can bring our marriage
back in union with Jehovah.’
I realized that it wasn’t what I wanted,
大事なのは
自分がどうしたいかではなく
but it was what Jehovah wanted.
エホバの望む通りにすることです
There was just no other choice.
また一緒になろう エホバに祝福して
いただけるよう頑張ろう と思いました
Jehovah wasn’t going to bless us
unless we got back together.
また一緒に暮らすようになっても
まだ努力が必要でした
When we got back together,
our marriage was still a work in progress.
この世に完璧な結婚などありませんが
You can’t have
a perfect marriage in this world,
but you can sure make it better
when you put Jehovah first.
エホバを第一にするなら
今より良いものにできます
We enjoyed the feelings
we had toward each other.
またデボラと心を通わせることが
できるようになりました
I felt closer to Debbie.
結婚して48年になります
Debbie and I
have been married now for 48 years.
別居していいことは 一つもありません
Separation does not make
anything better at all.
お互いを思い合う気持ちがちょっとでも
あるなら 頑張ってください
If you even have an inkling of love
for one another,
you want to work on that,
and you want to make it bloom
その努力は必ず実って
エホバは祝福してくださいます
so that Jehovah can bless it.
The blessings have been endless.
今は本当に祝福されています
Our children are all doing
子供たちはみんな
エホバに立派に仕えています
fantastic in the truth.
「エホバが善い神であることを
味わい知れ」とあります
Jehovah said:
“Taste and see that [He] is good.”
So we’ve got to do that.
そうしたいと思います
2人が私たちのために
We really appreciated this couple sharing
経験を話してくださったことを
their experience with the brotherhood.
心から感謝しています
He learned, you know.
兄弟は大切なことを学びました
They were always arguing,
2人はいつも言い争っていました
and that’s all they
did was argue, argue, argue.
言い争いが絶えませんでした
It affected their children.
子供たちにも悪い影響がありました
They decided to separate
and finally have peace.
2人は別居することにしました
もう一緒にいなくて済むので
‘I don’t have to be around her,’
or ‘I don’t have to be around him.’
「やっと平和になった」と思いました
But then he realized
his relationship with Jehovah
でも兄弟はエホバとの絆が
弱まっていることに気付きました
was being interfered with here,
and he went to the elders.
それで長老たちに援助を求めました
His prayers were affected.
祈りが聞かれないとも感じました
The things he noticed
—he was honest about that.
正直にそう言っています
And our precious sister
was so nice to honestly explain.
姉妹も自分が学んだことを
正直にこう言っていました
She said what she learned
was that ‘this is not about me;
「大事なのは 自分が
どうしたいかではなく
エホバの望む通りにすることです」
it’s about Jehovah.’
When you finally come to that realization,
このことに気付いて努力するなら
エホバは力を与え
Jehovah will strengthen you
配偶者と仲良くやっていけるよう
助けてくれるでしょう
to enjoy peace with your marriage partner.
では3つ目の点です
Now, the next one, I never tire of speaking
私は次の聖句を読むのが大好きです
about these particular couple of verses
この聖句について話すのも好きです
or reading about it or hearing
another brother give a talk about it.
他の兄弟たちがこの聖句について
話すのを聞くのも好きです
See, here’s what’s coming soon.
間もなく起きることが書かれています
Turn with me to 1 Thessalonians chapter 5.
テサロニケ第一 5章です
And many of you are going, ‘Oh, yeah, I know
皆さんの多くはぴんときたと思います
what he’s going to read about.’
ご一緒に読んでみましょう
And this is one of the prophecies
この預言はまだ実現していません
これから先に実現する預言です
that is yet to be fulfilled.
So it’s just invigorating
この聖句を読むとわくわくします
間もなく起きることが
書かれているからです
to know that soon
here’s what’s going to happen
—1 Thessalonians chapter 5,
テサロニケ第一 5:2, 3です
verses 2 and 3:
“For you yourselves know very well
こうあります 「エホバの日が
夜に忍び込む泥棒のように来ることを
皆さんはよく知っているからです
“that Jehovah’s day
is coming exactly as a thief in the night.
人々は 『平和だ 安全だ！』と
言っている時に
“Whenever it is that they are saying,
“‘Peace and security!’
突然滅ぼされることになります
“then sudden destruction
is to be instantly on them,
妊婦に起こる陣痛と同じように突然で
“just like birth pains on a pregnant woman,
and they will by no means escape.”
彼らは決して逃れられません」
Yes, see, “Jehovah’s day”
この「エホバの日」というのは
大患難のことです
—this has to do with the day
of the outbreak of the great tribulation
それは大いなるバビロンの滅びで始まり
when Babylon the Great is destroyed
ハルマゲドンで終わります
and Armageddon finishes it off.
この聖句の「エホバの日」というのは
その期間のことです
In this context, that’s “Jehovah’s day.”
And what happens before then
この「エホバの日」が始まる前に
次の宣言があります
is this proclamation, “peace and security!”
「平和だ 安全だ！」
Will religious leaders be involved?
この宣言にはサタンの体制の一部である
宗教指導者たちが関わるかもしれません
Well, they’re part of Satan’s system;
that’s very possible.
We’ll have to wait and see.
それが1つの宣言なのか
Will it be one announcement
or a series of announcements?
一連の宣言なのかは まだ分かりません
That we don’t know.
But this is coming.
でもこの宣言は必ず出されます
And those who are staying close to Jehovah
エホバとの絆を守り エホバとイエスが
与える平和を楽しんでいる人は
and enjoying the peace
from him and his Son, Jesus,
will not be deceived
この偽物の平和の宣言に
だまされることはありません
by this imitation proclamation of peace
それはサタンのうそだからです
全く信用できません
—imitation peace.
ではもう一度 マタイの4章を開いて
And again, back in Matthew chapter 4,
we’re going to see how Jesus handled
イエスがサタンの誘惑に
どう応じたか見てみましょう
this type of test from the Devil
and what we learn from it here
マタイ 4:8-11を
読んでみましょう
in verses 8-11 of Matthew chapter 4.
“Again the Devil took him [in verse 8]
こうあります 「さらに 悪魔は
イエスをとりわけ高い山に連れていき
“along to an unusually high mountain
世界の全ての王国と
その栄光を見せて 言った
“and showed him all the kingdoms
of the world and their glory.
“And he said to him:
“‘All these things I will give you
『ひれ伏して私を崇拝するなら
“if you fall down
and do an act of worship to me.’
これら全てをあげましょう』
その時 イエスは言った
［ためらわずに言いました］
“Then Jesus said to him [without hesitation]:
“‘Go away, Satan!
『離れ去れ サタン！
“‘For it is written:
“It is Jehovah your God you must worship,
「あなたが崇拝すべきなのは
エホバ神であり
この方だけに神聖な奉仕をしなければ
ならない」と書いてあるのです』
and it is to him alone
you must render sacred service.”’
その時 悪魔はイエスから離れた
“Then the Devil left him,
and look! angels came
すると 天使たちが来て
イエスに仕え始めた」
and began to minister to him.”
ここでも「と書いてあるのです」と
言いました 3度目です
Right away, a third time: “It is written.”
Jesus was having nothing to do
悪魔はイエスに
世界の王国とその栄光を見せて
with this offer of the kingdoms
—this imitation peace.
「全てをあげましょう」と言いましたが
イエスはきっぱりと退けました
‘You’ll have all the glory and rule.’
偽物の平和にすぎなかったからです
And it’s always boggled my mind
それにしても いつも思うんですが
that this one who knew
サタンは天にいた時の
イエスも知っていたのに
Jesus in his prehuman existence
would have the audacity to try to get Jesus
to bow down and worship him.
ひれ伏して自分を崇拝するようになどと
よくも言えたものです
It shows you that he’s obviously insane.
明らかに正気ではありません
イエスはサタンの申し出を退けました
Now, he wouldn’t allow it either
when they tried to make him an earthly king.
人々がご自分を王にしようとした時にも
そうしました
Jesus wasn’t having any part of that.
人々はイエスが平和を
実現してくれると思ったのです
They were thinking he could bring them peace.
But Jesus said there’s no peace
except by Jehovah’s way.
でもイエスはエホバの方法で
平和を実現させるつもりでした
神の王国が実現させる平和は
And the peace from God’s Kingdom
is so superior
人間が考え出すどんな平和よりも
はるかに優れています
to anything they could try to come up with
—their imitation peace.
本物の平和なのです
Here’s why.
なぜそう言えるでしょうか
Think about this:
Jesus will remove the Devil.
イエスは悪魔を除き去ります
Jesus will remove human rulership.
人間の支配も除き去ります
Jesus will remove sin.
罪も除き去ります
So the earth’s peace
will never again be disturbed.
地球の平和は
もう二度と脅かされません
And I appreciate very much
that he’s going to get rid of all problems,
うれしいことにイエスは
全ての問題を取り除いてくれます
イエスは痛みの原因全てを
取り除いてくれるのです
and that includes undoing all causes of pain
—and not just physical pain,
体の痛みだけではありません
emotional pain as well.
心の痛みもです
It’s wonderful to look forward to that time
お父さんエホバとイエスが与えてくれる
素晴らしい平和が実現する時が
with that beautiful peace
from our precious Father,
Jehovah, and his Son, Jesus.
本当に楽しみです
Now, in the following video,
では 次のビデオをご覧ください
see what convinced this sister
1人の姉妹はずっと探していた
本物の平和を見つけます
not to believe the world’s promises of peace.
どのようにでしょうか
父はいつも「平和をつくれるのは
神だけだ」と言っていました
My father always taught me
that we needed God in our life
in order for there to be peace.
クリスチャンが戦争をするのは
おかしい と考えていました
And he always wanted to know,
Can Christians go to war?
How is this consistent
with the Gospel of Jesus Christ?
キリストの教えと
全然違うじゃありませんか！
牧師は何も答えてくれませんでした
But the pastor could never give us an answer,
and so I thought I’d have to look
to politics to find it.
政治で何とかならないかと考えました
A lot of peace movements
were being formed at that time,
当時 平和運動が盛んで
私もある団体に入りました
so I joined one of them.
We decided where
the protest marches would be
どこでデモをするか
どんなチラシを配るか考えました
and which pamphlets we would use.
でも 抗議デモが終わった途端
But after the protests were over,
みんなハイになって
everyone was so excited
and they all started applauding
デモのリーダーたちの名前を
連呼しだしたんです
and cheering for the leaders.
こう思いました 「こんなのおかしい！
I thought:
‘That’s not what I wanted.
‘I don’t want to honor people.
人を持ち上げたいわけじゃない
‘I want to have world peace.
世界が平和になってほしい
And that still hasn’t happened yet.’
こんなんじゃ全然駄目！」
Then I started to feel very alone,
一人でもがいている気がしました
and it made me feel unsafe in this world.
不安になりました
With no peace in sight,
「自分は何を目指せば
いいんだろう」と思いました
I thought,
‘What is the purpose of life?’
While visiting friends for coffee,
I saw a man I’d never met before.
ある時 お茶に誘われて
友達の家に行ったら
見知らぬ男性がいました
My friends told me he wanted
to talk to us about the Bible.
聖書の話をしてくれるということでした
So I asked him:
それで 「クリスチャンが
軍隊に入るのは
“Sir, what do you think?
正しいんでしょうか」
と尋ねてみました
Can Christians join the military?”
And the man said,
“No, that’s not allowed
すると 「いいえ
聖書には『敵を愛しなさい』
とあります」と言われました
because the Bible says
you should ‘love your [enemy].’”
父が言っていたことを思い出しました
It made me think
about what my father always said
「神だけが平和をつくれる」
という言葉です
—that we need God to bring peace.
後日 すてきな女性が家に来て
Then a really nice lady came to my door,
and she had an orange book in her hand.
オレンジ色の本を見せてくれました
「真の平和と安全」という
言葉に目を奪われました
And it said:
True Peace and Security.
After reading it, I thought:
読み終えた時 「これだ！
‘This is it!
これこそ私が探していたものだ！」
と思いました
This is the organization
that truly wants peace.’
それで かつての仲間の所に行きました
So I went to those involved
in the peace movement.
そしてみんなに言いました
I told them that I believe
that God will change this world
「神が地球を楽園にしてくれる！
into a beautiful earth
where there’ll be true peace.
世界は平和になる！」
でも みんなから同情するような
目で見られました
They all looked at me
like I had lost my mind.
I was so happy with my new life.
今 とても幸せです
I felt like I was part of a family
お互いを本当に思いやる人たち
who truly cared about one another
平和を愛する人たちに囲まれています
and really wanted peace with each other.
Isaiah 14:7 had a major impact on my life
イザヤ 14:7の言葉が大好きです
神は 心から安らげる
平和な世界を約束しています
because there God promises
a calm and peaceful world.
本当の平和を見つけることができて
よかったですね
Wasn’t that nice how she learned?
She’d looked to politics and protests
for world peace.
以前は政治やデモに
望みをかけていました
Obviously, she was sincere.
とても真剣でした
でも そうしたものは
平和を実現できないことに気付きました
But she learned that’s all imitation peace.
True peace and security
comes from Jehovah God.
平和と安全を実現できるのは
エホバだけです
この話では
So wrapping it up with these
three different types
3種類の偽物の平和について
of imitation peace
that we’ve emphasized,
ご一緒に考えてきました
we want to encourage you
in these last minutes
ここからは少しの時間を使って
イエスが与えてくれる平和を
守ることについて考えます
to safeguard the peace
that Jesus has given you.
In John chapter 14
ヨハネ 14章です
よくご存じの聖句と思いますが
(you know this,
but I want you to really focus
6節の表現に特に注目したいと思います
on a particular point), in verse 6:
“Jesus said to him:
「イエスは言った 『私は道であり
真理であり 命です
“‘I am the way and the truth and the life.
No one comes to the Father
except through me.’”
私を通してでなければ 誰も
父のもとに行くことはできません』」
Isn’t that beautiful?
素晴らしい聖句です
Particularly we want to emphasize
Jesus is “the truth.”
特に注目したいのは
イエスが「真理」であるという点です
イエスの約束は全て信用できます
We can trust all of his promises.
He is “the truth.”
イエスは「真理」だからです
He’s going to give us peace
—already has—
イエスはこれまでも平和を与え
and will to a greater extent in the future.
これからもさらにそうしてくれます
Yes, our Master is “the truth.”
私たちの主イエスは「真理」です
And he gave the early Christians that peace.
イエスは初期クリスチャンにも
平和を与えました
The things that they were able to deal
with are just mind-boggling.
当時のクリスチャンは
大変な問題に直面しました
As we read the apostle Paul’s experiences
and Peter’s and others’
パウロもペテロも他の弟子たちも
—the persecution they endured—
they did it,
迫害を耐え忍ぶことができました
enduring with joy.
喜んでそうしたのです
It’s amazing!
そうできたのは イエスが弟子たちに
平和を与えていたからです
It can only be
a supernatural provision of peace.
And just remember,
イエスは私たちにも
平和を与えてくれます
Jesus will likewise give you
the peace you need now
それで私たちはエホバが望み
to keep doing Jehovah’s will
and to make Him happy.
喜ぶことを行い続けることができます
So, brothers, please,
では兄弟姉妹 ぜひ
イエスが与えてくれた
平和という贈り物を大切にしてください
safeguard the gift of peace
that Jesus has given you.
Satan uses this world
この体制を支配しているサタンは
to offer you promises of imitation peace.
平和を実現すると約束しています
でも 惑わされないでください
Do not be misled!
No, rather, “Let the peace of the Christ
rule in your hearts.”
むしろ 「キリストによる平和が
心に満ちるようにしましょう ⋯⋯
“And show yourselves thankful.”
感謝を表しましょう」
Yes, through his Son,
エホバはイエスを通して
Jehovah will bless us all with peace forever!
私たちがいつまでも平和を
楽しめるようにしてくださるのです
イエスが今も将来も
平和を与えてくださる という
Thank you, Brother Morris,
for strengthening our trust in Jesus’ promise
確信を強めることができました
to give us peace now and during the events
that will shortly take place.
モリス兄弟のお話に感謝いたします
The second session of our convention
has truly helped us
1日目の午後の部から
エホバがどのように
to see how Jehovah blesses us with peace.
平和を与えてくださるかを
学ぶことができました
2日目の午前の部では
どんなことを学べるでしょうか
What can we look forward to
in the next session?
2日目のテーマは
ペテロ第二 3:14の次の言葉です
The scripture theme will be
from 2 Peter 3:14:
“Be found . . . spotless and unblemished
and in peace.”
「汚点も傷もない平和な人と
神に認めていただ［く］」
The program will begin with a symposium
that will help prepare us
最初のシンポジウムでは
「平和の良い知らせ」を
あらゆる機会に伝えるのに
役立つ事柄を学ぶことができます
to share the “good news of peace”
at every opportunity.
Young ones can look forward
to a special talk just for them
若い皆さんは
統治体の兄弟がしてくださる
特別な話を ぜひ楽しみにしてください
given by a member of the Governing Body.
世界のいろいろな場所で 病気や
経済的な問題や自然災害に直面しながら
We’ll also see how brothers and sisters
are maintaining their peace
even when suffering from illness,
economic problems,
平和な心を持ち続けている
兄弟姉妹の様子も見ることができます
natural disasters, and other difficulties.
And of course, our next session
includes the baptism talk,
午前の部のハイライトの1つは
バプテスマの話です
after which those who have been approved
話の後 それぞれの場所で
バプテスマが行われます
will be baptized locally.
We have much to look forward to!
本当に楽しみですね
To conclude today’s session,
今日のプログラムの結びに
112番の歌を歌いましょう
let’s sing song number 112, entitled
「エホバは平和の神」という歌です
“Jehovah, God of Peace.”
Again, that’s song number 112.
もう一度言います 112番です
After the song concludes,
you may have your own closing prayer.
歌い終わったら
それぞれ祈りを捧げてください